<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Biking</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/feeds/biking.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://archive.reputablejournal.com/</id><updated>2016-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Biking with Blaise</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/biking-with-blaise.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-06-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2016-06-13:/biking-with-blaise.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blaise Schaeffer, my former student for all of 3 weeks, is on a cross country bike journey. He was riding right past my lake house on Bone Lake, and so I got to participate in his adventure for 40 miles! It was awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blaise started the day in North Branch …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blaise Schaeffer, my former student for all of 3 weeks, is on a cross country bike journey. He was riding right past my lake house on Bone Lake, and so I got to participate in his adventure for 40 miles! It was awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blaise started the day in North Branch Minnesota, and texted me when he got to Balsam Lake WI, I texted him back that I would meet him at Jonzy's Market and we would go from there. The plan was to ride to Cumberland where we would be picked up by his mom Deb. But she was running a bit behind schedule so rather than hang around the Cumberland quick trip for an hour we extended our ride to Haugen Wisconsin.  You’ll probably have to look that one up on a map.  That made it a 41 mile ride for me and about 80 for Blaise. 
&lt;img alt="" src="/images/BlaiseBrad.jpg"&gt;
It was a great chance to ride and talk to Blaise about everything he’s seen and done on this trip.  You should check out his blog to get an idea:  &lt;a href="http://blaise2s.com" title="Blaise2s.com"&gt;blaise2s.com&lt;/a&gt;.  He told me about many of the amazing hosts he has had along the way due to the &lt;a href="http://www.warmshowers.org"&gt;Warm Showers&lt;/a&gt; network.  Warm Showers is an online community of cyclists and hosts who are willing to have people like Blaise stay in their home overnight while they are on a long distance cycle adventure.  Great idea!&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Biking"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>new commuting strategy</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/new-commuting-strategy.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-10-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2011-10-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2011-10-08:/new-commuting-strategy.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I can see the campus from my house, its about a 20 minute walk, all downhill for the first half of the trek, then slightly uphill the rest of the way to the Olin building. &amp;nbsp;I've always thought that biking to work would be the way to go, but I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I can see the campus from my house, its about a 20 minute walk, all downhill for the first half of the trek, then slightly uphill the rest of the way to the Olin building. &amp;nbsp;I've always thought that biking to work would be the way to go, but I hate getting home all sweaty and gross. &amp;nbsp;The problem is the uphill trek. &amp;nbsp;From the River to My House is about a 300 foot climb over the course of just under a mile, a 6% grade for those who care to know. &amp;nbsp;But trust me, its steep. &amp;nbsp;It takes a lot of work to get up to my house, even on my road bike.&lt;br /&gt;But, awhile back I was reading about some of the new electric assist bikes, and I thought hey, I haven't bought a new bike in a long time. &amp;nbsp;So, I started doing a bit more research and decided that one of the Trek Ride+ bikes would be great. &amp;nbsp;I ended up with the Trek FX+. &amp;nbsp;Sadly, my local bike shop can't sell the Ride+ bikes, so I had to go to La Crosse to find this one. &amp;nbsp;The good news is that this is a good time of the year to get a new bike! &amp;nbsp; 30% off was the sale today.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img alt="Trek FX+" border="0" height="223" src="http://lh4.ggpht.com/-oz5YYOkYY18/TpDG6iClFzI/AAAAAAAAAag/ngLF-wLwNTA/2011-10-08_16-13-01_814.jpg?imgmax=800" title="2011-10-08_16-13-01_814.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I took it for a ride around LaCross and up the only little hill I could find, &amp;nbsp;the Cass Ave Bridge, not much of a hill, but I knew I was on to something when I felt like I was riding on the flats with the wind at my back, when I was actually going up a little hill. &amp;nbsp;After riding it around downtown a little longer I went back to the shop, smitten. &amp;nbsp;The only decision was which panniers to get so I can haul groceries and my stuff to school.&lt;br /&gt;Jane hasn't ridden it yet, but I have the feeling I know what she'll want for Mothers day. &amp;nbsp;This would be the perfect option for our cycling marriage. &amp;nbsp;I could ride my road bike and she could ride the electric assist. &amp;nbsp;I think I see some longer bike rides together in our future :-)&lt;br /&gt;The other great thing is that no gas is required. &amp;nbsp;Its all battery operated, and as I coast down the hill the battery is recharged. &amp;nbsp;I'lll be able to easily cruise my way to school, and then on the way home I can engage the electric drive at the bottom of the hill, and get the assistance I need to climb up to my house. &amp;nbsp;I won't arrive home sweaty, and I'll have the satisfaction of knowing that I got a few extra minutes of exercise, and didn't use any gas! &amp;nbsp;The only downside is that I'll be only inches away from the Whippy Dip as I ride home, but as long as I can get by there I'll be fine.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-7356015564165588778?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Biking"></category><category term="biking"></category></entry><entry><title>polk county biking</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/polk-county-biking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-21T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-07-21T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-07-21:/polk-county-biking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a quiz for you... What do deer, old cars, a saw mill, and black bears all have in common?  These are all things I regularly see on my rides around polk county.  The countryside by our cabin is some of the best riding around, every road is paved and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here's a quiz for you... What do deer, old cars, a saw mill, and black bears all have in common?  These are all things I regularly see on my rides around polk county.  The countryside by our cabin is some of the best riding around, every road is paved and very lightly travelled.  I can ride around any number of lakes and have all kinds of flexibility to make a route that is anywhere from 12 to 50 miles long.  Bone Lake, Half Moon, Pipe, Balsam, Little Blake, Butternut, these are a few of the lakes that I loop in and through on a regular basis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So, the other night I took my camera for a ride and focused more on the picture taking that the riding.  Here's my favorite shot from the night and you can find the rest of them &lt;a href="http://www.facebook.com/album.php?aid=2064788&amp;id=59203846&amp;l=2defc9fdd3"&gt;here:&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src="http://lh3.ggpht.com/_wISL1SSAaEA/TEcaYq9NsuI/AAAAAAAAAH4/fbqhEL_1Zj0/IMG_1264.jpg?imgmax=800" alt="IMG_1264.jpg" title="IMG_1264.jpg" border="0" width="518" height="345" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Incidentally, this picture illustrates where the bear comes in to the picture.  This little pond is at the bottom of a little hill and around a nice little corner.  One morning a came coasting down the hill and around the corner to see a black bear, he would have been right in the bottom right corner of the picture.  I don't know which of us was more surprised!  The bear took off one way and I took off as fast as I could up the hill and past the pond.  We've never seen each other again.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-1629252102942453605?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Biking"></category><category term="biking"></category></entry><entry><title>a mid-winter cycling treat</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/a-mid-winter-cycling-treat.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-01-21T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2009-01-21T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2009-01-21:/a-mid-winter-cycling-treat.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although the weather back home may have been below zero, in Northern california he sun was out and it was 68 degrees.  Perfect weather for a bikeride.  So after talking to the nice folks at the Palo Alto Bike Shop &lt;a href="http://wlgregg.blogspot.com/"&gt;Wes&lt;/a&gt; and I rented a couple of nice demo road …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although the weather back home may have been below zero, in Northern california he sun was out and it was 68 degrees.  Perfect weather for a bikeride.  So after talking to the nice folks at the Palo Alto Bike Shop &lt;a href="http://wlgregg.blogspot.com/"&gt;Wes&lt;/a&gt; and I rented a couple of nice demo road bikes from Calmar bikes in Santa Clara.  Calmar is right by our hotel and the staff there was super friendly and helpful in getting us set up for a ride.  Incidentally Calmar has no relation to Calmar IA.  I road a nice Spanish BH RoadROM and Wes road a hot pink Trek Pilot 5.2.  Even though the bike was pink we felt pretty good passing all the californians on the way up Old La Honda Road.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rather than head out from the hotel on the busy city streets I decided to take Novian's advice and head into the foothills west of Palo Alto.  You can see the ride we took on the map below.  This is from a cool website called mapmyride.com that I will use in the future for keeping track of my rides.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe src="http://js.mapmyfitness.com/embed/blogview.html?r=b4f0f6cf8357a604ae5acdd7a337b17e&amp;amp;u=e&amp;amp;t=ride" frameborder="0" height="700" width="100%"&gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;a href="http://www.mapmyride.com/ride/united-states/ca/-palo-alto/752308357021"&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;01/18/2009 Skyline Drive with Wes Gregg&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;/a&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;br/&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;a href="http://www.mapmyride.com/find-ride/united-states/ca/-palo-alto"&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;Find more Bike Rides in  Palo Alto, California&amp;amp;amp;amp;lt;/a&amp;amp;amp;amp;gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;!-- MMF PARTNER TOOL --&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The ride was just beautiful even though we had to climb 2500 feet to get to the view.  On the way up we road through some big redwood trees.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/34342503@N02/3211490966" title="View 'Redwoods on Old La Honda Road' on Flickr.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://static.flickr.com/3342/3211490966_9285179f1e.jpg" alt="Redwoods on Old La Honda Road" align="left" border="0" height="" width="" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Once you get on Skyline drive you can see the ocean on one side and the Valley on the other.  Here's me, I look more tired in the picture than I actually felt!  Really, Honest!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/34342503@N02/3209692219" title="View 'Brad -- Looks tired after the long climb' on Flickr.com"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3400/3209692219_57f086c6d7.jpg" alt="Brad -- Looks tired after the long climb" align="left" border="0" height="375" width="500" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The rest of the ride is a long coast down Page Mill Road and then some flat riding past the Stanford Dish and the Stanford Golf course.  It would have been fun to stop and play 18 holes but I didn't have my clubs with me.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-330069778560682480?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Biking"></category><category term="siliconvalley"></category><category term="biking"></category></entry></feed>