<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - CityLife</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/feeds/citylife.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://archive.reputablejournal.com/</id><updated>2018-10-27T10:20:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>City Life</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/one_month.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-10-27T10:20:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T10:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2018-10-27:/one_month.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One month into our big adventure of living in downtown Minneapolis and we are loving it!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Its a misty late October morning, the farmers market isn't open yet, and the Liverpool Cardiff match is on the TV.  Below us the runners for the Halloween half are spread out on West River Road. We are a little sleepy as it was 11:30 by the time we got home from &amp;quot;Beautiful&amp;quot; the Carol King story playing at the Orpheum.  We love our city life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Minneapolis/stone_arch.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;We love our view of the Stone Arch Bridge!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We moved in on September 24 and the rain started on the 25th and continued for two and a half weeks.  But once the weather cleared up we have taken advantage of some clear fall days to discover our new neighborhood.  A bike trail across the road leads to the &amp;quot;Dinky Town Greenway&amp;quot; which gives us a clear path to walk to TCF stadium in under 30 minutes!  I swear we have waited that long to get out of the parking lot after a Loons game in the past!  Even better were these views taken on a sunset walk home.  We love our city life!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Minneapolis/blue_35w.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Sunset view of the 35W bridge from the old Northern Pacific railroad bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Minneapolis/washingtonave.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Looking the other way at the Washington Ave. Bridge&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything in downtown is walkable, but within a few blocks we have Thai restaurants, great breweries/brew pubs, fine dining, the Guthrie theater, and so much more. There is even a giant stadium, should we ever renew our interest in the Vikings.  By bike its less than 10 minutes to the computer science building at the University of Minnesota.  With access to hundreds of miles of bike trails right out our back door, I can't wait for warmer weather.  I've biked over to Macalester for a lecture and I'm looking forward to attending talks and colloquia at the U of M.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our 1500 square feet is perfect for our needs.  A den for me to use as my office and reading area, an awesome kitchen and a nice living room for sitting or watching TV.  In the morning the shared workout room is an awesome place to workout and watch the sun light up the IDS and Wells Fargo buildings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Minneapolis/kitchen.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Our new Kitchen is awesome&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="/images/Minneapolis/livingroom.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;We were able to keep our comfy furniture from Decorah.  The walls could use some color but its very comfortable.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane and I have been slowly reconnecting with friends, family, and former students from around the twin cities, and we look forward to continuing that trend after we get back from upcoming travels.  We have enjoyed overnight visits from some of our Decorah friends with more visits to breweries and even an awesome escape room last weekend.  Although I've been super busy with Runestone Interactive and Google, I am looking forward to some downtime and travel in a week.  I left graduation at Luther in May and flew to Mountain View the same day!  The following day I was hard at work on site at Google!  Its been 40+ hour weeks ever since.  Speaking of travel, we already love the fact that we will be able to take our bags and make the short walk to the light rail to the airport.  No parking, and no home maintenance worries while we are away.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="CityLife"></category><category term="Life"></category><category term="Minneapolis"></category></entry></feed>