<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Cooking</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/feeds/cooking.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/</id><updated>2014-05-10T21:36:09+00:00</updated><entry><title>The Sous Vide Adventure Begins</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/the-sous-vide-adventure-begins.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-05-10T21:36:09+00:00</published><updated>2014-05-10T21:36:09+00:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2014-05-10:/PelicanBlog/the-sous-vide-adventure-begins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;section id="id1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Sous-vide adventure begins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were in Las Vegas last fall, I had the most delicious steak I’ve ever eaten. It was at Bobby Flay’s Mesa Grill.  This blew me away. Although I love a good steak at a restaurant, usually I can do just as well …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/section&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;section id="id1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Sous-vide adventure begins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we were in Las Vegas last fall, I had the most delicious steak I’ve ever eaten. It was at Bobby Flay’s Mesa Grill.  This blew me away. Although I love a good steak at a restaurant, usually I can do just as well at home.  But this steak was amazing.  This was a two inch think tenderloin that was perfectly medium rare from edge to edge! The very outside edge was seared perfectly too.  Whoa, I thought at the time,  how did they do that?  How can you have a steak so uniformly done?  The answer of course is Sous-vide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, I’ve been reading the books, like &lt;em&gt;Modernist Cuisine at Home&lt;/em&gt;, and lots of articles on “Serious Eats”, I’ve seen it done on &lt;em&gt;Chopped&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Iron Chef&lt;/em&gt;.  Then the other day I got a Kickstarter notice about the new Anova Precision Cooker.  Its an immersion circulator that lets you do sous-vide cooking without one of the big fancy sous-vide appliances.  This just clips on the edge of one of your big pots, and away you go.  Alton Brown would love it.   Unfortunately this new fancy one that even connects to your iPhone will not be available  until later this year, so I decided to give the Nomiku a try.  It was the highest rated of three options on Amazon, and was Prime Eligible.  If I really like it I figure I can always upgrade to the Anova later.  So here's my setup for an afternoon of high-tech cooking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/SousVideSetup.JPG" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind sous-vide cooking is that you can cook at a lower temperature for a longer period of time.  bringing the water and your food into equilibrium.  Whats cool about that is that you can cook a steak to exactly 132 degrees, and you can leave it go for an extra hour or two and it will remain at the perfect medium rare done-ness.  You can also cook chicken. without heating it to 165 degrees!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What!?  I thought?  this cannot be.  But then I started to do some reading and once again science rocks.  &lt;a class="m-link-wrap" href="http://www.seriouseats.com/2010/04/sous-vide-basics-low-temperature-chicken.html"&gt;http://www.seriouseats.com/2010/04/sous-vide-basics-low-temperature-chicken.html&lt;/a&gt;  It turns out that you can kill all the nasty bacteria at 135 degrees, it just takes longer!  Like 90 minutes!  Heating chicken to 165 kills the bacteria too, instantly.  But it also gives you dry chicken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other aspect of sous vide is that you use a vacuum sealer to seal your food in plastic before you immerse it in the water.  This allows you to season the food and add aromatics to your bag.  Yum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this also precipitated a quick trip to the hardware store to get a FoodSaver vacuum sealer.  Yay more kitchen toys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now, I’m trying a steak.  I sealed it up and dropped it in.  In a couple of hours I’ll get out the cast iron skillet and heat it up good and hot, so that I can sear the meat when it comes out.  A glass of Rombaur and a baked potato and I’m all set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="Cooking"></category><category term="Cooking"></category></entry><entry><title>pizza oven</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/pizza-oven.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2011-09-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2011-09-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2011-09-20:/PelicanBlog/pizza-oven.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love it when a good plan comes together. &amp;nbsp;Last summer we decided to finally take the plunge and build a pizza oven at the lake. &amp;nbsp;After looking at the options to site the oven, and thinking about a fireplace/oven combination, we finally decided to combine the pizza oven …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love it when a good plan comes together. &amp;nbsp;Last summer we decided to finally take the plunge and build a pizza oven at the lake. &amp;nbsp;After looking at the options to site the oven, and thinking about a fireplace/oven combination, we finally decided to combine the pizza oven project with our desire to replace the aging and increasingly ugly outdoor bar area.&lt;br /&gt;In late June I contacted a few different stone masons to start to get an idea of cost and availability. &amp;nbsp;I was immediately impressed with David Marek&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href="http://draft.blogger.com/www.layersofstone.com"&gt;www.layersofstone.com&lt;/a&gt; and his ideas on the project. &amp;nbsp;I checked some references and decided that my initial impression was correct, that David would be a good guy to work with. &amp;nbsp;Here's his original sketch of our project.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img alt="Brad Miller Plan" border="0" height="331" src="http://lh5.ggpht.com/-Akb0ivIiOQI/TnixuYBvTlI/AAAAAAAAAYw/NFDsPjnfh68/Brad%252520Miller%252520Plan.jpg?imgmax=800" style="float: left;" title="Brad Miller Plan.jpg" width="600" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;David was able to start tearing out the old bar, and working on the replacement the last week of July. &amp;nbsp;He just finished the project last week, in time for us to enjoy some Pizza with our friends this last weekend. &amp;nbsp;The result was beyond my expectations. &amp;nbsp;Here's a photo of the final outcome that you can compare with the plan:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;img alt="6162728834 2a3c8d4985" border="0" height="333" src="http://lh6.ggpht.com/-rxZ0eI9DcHo/TnixvImNP2I/AAAAAAAAAY0/7drzQ7ZYWPU/6162728834_2a3c8d4985.jpg?imgmax=800" style="float: left;" title="6162728834_2a3c8d4985.jpg" width="500" /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For more shots of the project you can check out my &lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonelake/sets/72157627580626967/"&gt;Flickr Photo Set&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Last saturday was the inaugural pizza baking. &amp;nbsp;It took about two hours to get the oven fully up to temperature, but the wait was well worth it. &amp;nbsp;We used this &lt;a href="http://recipepad.appspot.com/showrecipe/aglyZWNpcGVwYWRyDgsSBlJlY2lwZRiRpA4M"&gt;crust recipe&lt;/a&gt; and pre-baked the crusts on both sides for just a few seconds. &amp;nbsp;The crusts came out very light and crunchy. &amp;nbsp;I'm looking forward to trying out lots of different crust recipes, but this was definitely a winner.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-2405740608151021074?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Cooking"></category><category term="cabin"></category></entry><entry><title>in praise of the two fat ladies</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/in-praise-of-the-two-fat-ladies.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2010-11-06:/PelicanBlog/in-praise-of-the-two-fat-ladies.html</id><content type="html">&lt;div class='posterous_autopost'&gt;via &lt;a href="http://www.amateurgourmet.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Amateur Gourmet&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/TheAmateurGourmet/~3/mD5f39j3gCo/in_praise_of_the_two_fat_ladies.html"&gt;&lt;img src="http://www.amateurgourmet.com/assets_c/2010/11/clarissMS2508_468x327-thumb-425x296-1188.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;Mr. Game Show was a Hanukkah gift that my parents bought me one year in the 1980s. It looked like a regular board game (small ... &lt;a href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/TheAmateurGourmet/~3/mD5f39j3gCo/in_praise_of_the_two_fat_ladies.html"&gt;Read More &gt;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-6114793939386260196?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Cooking"></category></entry></feed>