<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Migration20</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/feeds/migration20.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://archive.reputablejournal.com/</id><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Boondocking in Goosenecks</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/boondocking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-14:/boondocking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A short day of driving gets us a great reward!  Goosenecks does not take reservations but we got there in time to get a primo campsite!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Goosenecks state park in Utah has, no electric hookup, no water, and no dump station for our black or gray water, and no lights. What it does have are eight incredible camp sites with unparalleled views of the desert plateau and the river.  You have probably seen photos of “Horseshoe Bend” in the Colorado River, Gooseneck is that -- times three!  Our site was situated right at the end of one of those bends and our campsite was right on the edge of the cliff looking down into the river&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/goosenecks_view.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We arrived at Goosnecks just after lunch time, so we made ourselves a quick salad lunch and ate it in our lawn chairs right at the edge of the cliff.  Our most beautiful lunch location yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch we took a little drive.  Jane has the soul of a jeep owner and always wants to take our car onto the most interesting side roads -- most of them unpaved!  In this case the drive was through the Valley of the Gods scenic backcountry area.  It is 17  miles of dirt/gravel road.  It was slow going but very pretty.  But mostly I was grumpy as I was wishing that I was on my fat tire bike instead of experiencing this inside of a car!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/valley_drive.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the drive we just took it easy around the campsite.  I took my bike to the far end of the campground to take a picture of our campsite looking back over the canyon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/campsite_cliff.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon it was happy hour and I tried a Gin and Tonic with my new Gin from Moab.  It is a barell finished gin so it has a slightly dark tint to it and is just on the edge of having a whisky like taste.  I started marinating some pork for supper and soon happy hour stretched out into sunset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/goosenecks_sunset.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After dinner we got to really enjoy the lack of light pollution and enjoy the stars!  The Milky Way was in full view from horizon to horizon!  We attempted some night photography to capture the beauty but it really doesn’t do it justice.  The night sky was our entertainment for the night and so we turned in knowing that we would head out for Sedona, AZ early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/milky_way.png" /&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Camping"></category></entry><entry><title>Sunrise in Canyonlands</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/sunrise_mesa_arch.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-12:/sunrise_mesa_arch.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An early morning to watch the sun rise through Mesa Arch in Canyonlands is amazing!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/mesa_sunrise_wide.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we arrived the parking log at Mesa Arch was nearly full and it was not yet 6:30AM.  It is a short hike back from the lot and we were greeted with a lineup of people already in position with their tripods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/early_tripods.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the minutes stretched out the horizon began to glow and the stars began to disappear.  More people began to show up and everyone was just whispering to each other so as not to break the spell of beauty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/horizon_glow.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the time for sunrise 7:25 got closer and closer the noise level behan to rise as the excitement for the sun to appear continued to grow.  When the sun did appear, right on time someone made the comment, &amp;quot;Wow those scientists really know their stuff. #SCIENCE.&amp;quot;  It gave me my first chuckle of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/glowing_arch.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after this people started to leave, back to their campers for coffee and eggs.  We stuck around a little longer to enjoy the beautiful light in the canyon below the arch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/arch_frame.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was really hard to let go of the scene, but the day awaits us. Later this morning we will leave Dead Horse state park and head to an RV park in the heart of Moab.  We are Looking forward to trying some brews at the brewery.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>Arches National Park</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/arches_np.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-11:/arches_np.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;An early morning to to make sure we got in at Arches pays off.  We did our big hiking before the heat and got to see everything we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/brad_delicate.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we were not enthusiastic at the agreed upon hour of 5:30 to get ourselves out of bed and head out to the park it was well worth the effort.  We arrived at Arches National Park and headed through the gate in darkness, but by the time we got to the parking lot for Delicate Arch it was light enough to see and hike.  We headed out of the parking lot for a 3 mile round trip hike described as strenuous.  It was mostly uphill on the way to the arch so it seemed to live up to its billing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rounding the final curve it is really quite amazing to see this arch.  We climbed over the wall and just took it all in enjoying the mostly quiet atmosphere.  Until someone dropped both of their water bottles! That broke the silence for quite some time as they clattered and clanged all the way down the bowl you see in this picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/delicate_basin.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jane told me to get in line so she could take my picture under the arch.  Since she and Shirley had already done this last year she was content to just soak in the scenery.  Standing in line is never my favorite thing to do but people around me were friendly (and socially distant) so it passed the time.  One guy joked he wanted to climb to the top of the arch, I said &amp;quot;someone has to water that plant,&amp;quot;  and that broke the ice with everyone riffing on climbing or getting arrested or whatever.  In a general spirit of cooperation everyone was wearing masks, but still willing to handle the iPhones of the people in front of them to take pictures under the arch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After my solo picture at the arc we took a selfie and headed on our way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/delicate_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a brief detour to climb up to a window that allowed you to see Delicate Arch.  It was great except the wind was blowing so hard it nearly knocked me off my feet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/delicate_view.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From delicate arch we enjoyed the drive to Devils Garden. Stopping at several viewpoints along the way.  The highlight of Devils garden is the Landscape Arch which really looks like it should fall at any moment.  We also got to see some other arches that were closer to the parking lot, including the beautiful pine tree arch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/pine_tree_arch.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/arch_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, the wind had really picked up and the horizon was threatening rain, but we had one last stop for the day - The Windows.  The turnoff for the window is right next to balanced rock.  Which is the size of THREE School Busses!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/balanced_rock.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point we had been hiking and touring for about six hours, and even though it was just 1PM we decided to call it a day and head back to the camper.  Sometimes vacationing is so exhausting!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>Oh What Massive Cliffs We Know Now</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/canyonlands.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-10:/canyonlands.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A false start at Arches leads to a good day in Canyonlands.  With a bonus mountain bike ride!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/canyonlands1.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the day like we were on vacation.  Wake up, make some coffee and tea, warm up some of our delicious birds nest breakfasts in the microwave, and then head out for Arches National Park.  The bad news is it is Saturday and the crowds we saw in Moab yesterday all beat us to Arches! When we got there the sign said Park Closed, come back in three hours. Ugh! 20 miles of driving for nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully Canyonlands is only four miles from the entrance to Dead Horse so we headed back there instead.  With one small booth to handle all of the cars entering the park the line there stretched back for half a mile! It took us nearly 40 minutes to get to the front of the line and since we have a national park pass we were waved right through. If only everyone had a pass!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we were in the park, it was all good.  I didn't know how influential Uranium mining had been to this area.  Nor did I know that the Cisco Kid was a Uranium titan and not an outlaw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As long as we are on things I didn't know here is one for you. Can you guess the meaning behind this phrase?  &amp;quot;Oh What Massive Cliffs We Know Now&amp;quot;  While there are certainly plenty of massive cliffs in Canyonlands, this is a mnemonic device to help you remember 200 million years of geologic history that you can see in the park, starting with the oldest to the youngest...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organ Rock Shale, White Rim Sandstone, Moenkopi Formation,Chinle Formation, Wingate Sandstone, Kayenta Formation, Navaho Sandstone.  If you want to know more check out &lt;a href="https://www.nps.gov/cany/learn/nature/organrockshale.htm"&gt;The National Park Service Page on Canyonlands&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the False Kiva hike.  It was good but &amp;quot;inverted&amp;quot; all downhill to start and then a big climb to finish.  It tired out our legs too early for what we saw.  which was a closed site because of Vandalism!  Please people do not vandalize the national parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there we went to Upheaval Dome which was pretty awesome. In the middle of all of this red stone you get a dome like this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/upheaval_dome.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of theories on how this amazing formation came to be.  The salt dome theory and the meteorite theory.  To me the former seems more likely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/UD_hike.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After many hours of hiking and enjoying the vistas in Canyonlands we were tired.  And while my wife still wanted to drive our car on the Shafer trail I was against the idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/Shafer_trail.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we went back to the camper and relaxed.  Well not quite!  I had been dieing to try out the mountain bike trails in the campground.  I have my fat tire bike with, so it was a great chance to try out some real mountain biking!  I thought it would be just some dirt trails, but noooo there were rocks and dropoffs and logs and obstacles everywhere.  It was fun!  But it was terrifying and my hands were cramped from gripping the handlebars too tight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/MB_rocks.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/MB_parking.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well then we relaxed until just before sunset.  We hopped in the car and drove up to Dead horse point to watch the sun go down.  It was great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/DHP_sunset.png" /&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>Dead Horse State Park</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/deadhorse1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-09:/deadhorse1.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are in Utah!  What can you do with all of this amazing, rugged territory except leave it for people to hike in and enjoy!  Thank you Utah, Thank you Teddy Roosevelt!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/brad_ledge2.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We left Glenwood Springs this morning and headed into Utah!  The stark difference between Utah and Colorado is just stunning.  Both beautiful but in such different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was attempting to participate in the Concordia College board of regents meeting on my phone and iPad from the car but the signal gets a bit spotty when you get into the canyonlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moab was a mad house! Road construction and crowds of people showing up for the marathon this weekend created a traffic jam that was miles long!  Because our campsite does not have water we had to navigate the craziness to find the gas station that gives away drinking water.  We were the third camper in line when we showed up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we had to navigate back through all the traffic again to go to Dead Horse State Park.  After getting the camper situated we headed out to hike the west rim trail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my favorites from the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/deadhorse_best.png" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Beautiful horseshoe bend in the river.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/deadhorse_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A Dead Horse selfie&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3089.png" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A Dead Horse View&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure class="m-figure"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3095.png" /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A Dead Horse View&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Judging Someone by their Cover</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/emerald_lake.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-07:/emerald_lake.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow! I have done a lot of great hikes in my day but this hike in Rocky Mountain National Park is one of the most moving and beautiful yet.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3062.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hike to Emerald Lake may be one of the most scenic hikes I have ever done.  It was about two miles from the Bear Lake parking lot and we walked around two other lakes on our way in the golden hour of morning sunlight.  The trail was not paved and fairly narrow, not even wide enough for two of us to walk side by side very comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing that really struck me about this hike was how many people were wearing their cover.  At least 90% of the people we met on the trail, outside, were wearing a mask.  Lots of people had them on as a “chin strap,”  until they saw you coming on the trail and then up the masks went.  Being out on the trail like that I really felt the sense from everyone that they were saying that they cared about the health and well being of others by the simple act of wearing a mask.   Thank you kind strangers!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those that didn’t I found myself getting a little judgmental.  What makes you better than the rest of us that you won’t wear a mask?  Dear God, are you a Trump supporter making a statement?  Note this is during the time that our &amp;quot;dear&amp;quot; president should be in quarantine due to his own active case of COVID-19.  It is just the day after his infamous photo op on the white house balcony, where he rips off his mask!  I'm sure some of the non-mask wearers were perfectly nice people, some may have not thought about it thinking they were outside, but most just seemed so indifferent!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But enough of the politics of mask wearing.  The scenery was amazing.  Here are some of my favorites from the hike.  Yes just some!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3042.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3046.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3048.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3049.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3051.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3053.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3054.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3056.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3059.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3060.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3062.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3063.png" /&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/IMG_3064.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, sorry, that was a lot but it is really hard to pick!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Bible Point</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/bible_point.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-05T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-05:/bible_point.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were just two kids, so young and so in love.  Today it was so fun to relive a moment from 37 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/bible_point.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the map you will see that Estes Park Colorado is not on a line between Sun Valley and Luverne Minnesota.  Thirty seven years ago a nineteen year old boy begged, pleaded, pouted, and cajoled his parents into making a detour to Rocky Mountain National Park on their way home from a conference in Sun Valley Idaho.  The object of this detour was a girl.  A girl they had never met, but who their son was pretty crazy about.  The detour only allowed for a one night visit, but the girl remains to this day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/aspens.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, in fact, we recreated one of our activities from the detour, the hike to Bible Point at YMCA of the Rockies.  Thirty seven years ago we took a selfie, on film, using the timer on the camera.  Jane made a craft project out of that picture in a heart shaped frame with the word Forever painted on the frame.  We still have the picture and the frame, and now we have a new selfie to add to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/bible_point_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the scenery was even more beautiful than I remembered it!  Of course I wasn't really looking at the scenery 37 years ago I was mostly looking at the girl.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a short drive from Boyd Lake State Park to Rocky Mountain National Park.  It was all uphill and the challenge we had been waiting for; to see if the Audi could manage the uphill pull of the camper in the mountains.  No Problem!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back at the campground we climbed the small hill behind our camper and watched the sun set over the mountains.  With the smoke in the air from all of the forest fires it was pretty spectacular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/elk_rmnp.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time of year is pretty popular because it is the &amp;quot;Elk rut&amp;quot;  It is a very interesting sound that the male moose makes as it claims a herd of does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/turkeys.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course we see wild turkeys all the time in Wisconsin, but these just looked a little bigger and a little more interesting!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>Custer State Park</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/custer_sp.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-03:/custer_sp.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lots of great sights in Custer State Park.  The Black Hills loop, and hiking with Josh, Rachel and Maple.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/legion_lake.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day started with an early morning phone call.  Jane's dad Len passed away peacefully during the night.  This was not unexpected as he had had several strokes and nobody wanted him to linger.  He was 95 years old, he lived a good life and touched a lot of people including his many students over his long teaching career.  He was ready to be with Betty again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We considered a lot of options and discussed timelines with the rest of the family.  In the end we decided to have the funeral on the 24th of October.  This allows us to complete our trip to Indio and gives the grandchildren some time to adjust work schedules.  The funeral will be a small family graveside service in Saint James.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We did the Black Hills loop drive today starting with Iron Mountain road and returning on the Needles Highway.  Iron Mountain has some amazing tunnels that perfectly frame the presidents and some amazing pigtail bridges. I had never considered that roads required architects but these roads did have an architect and it shows.  Every turn brings more beautiful scenery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/tunnel_pres.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here the architect designed the tunnel so that it perfectly frames the monument as you approach and drive through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/pigtail_bridge.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of one of the pigtail bridges that spiral under each other!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had so many great views of the monument on the drive that we really didn't see any reason to join the masses of people at the site itself.  Instead we continued on, and briefly visited the Crazy Horse monument.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/sylvan_lake.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had lunch at Sylvan Lake.  There was a nice one mile hike around the lake that was very scenic.  We then continued along the Needles highway to get back to our campsite at Legion Lake.  We have a reservation at the Sylvan Lake campsite for next summer's trip, but we noticed that there was no cell service in the area -- probably due to all the giant granite spires!  We love the Legion Lake campground and we may switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The highlight of the day was the arrival of Josh, Rachel, and Maple!  They are at the end of a week-long trip to Colorado and decided to meet us in Custer on their way home.  We did another short hike around Legion Lake with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/Josh_Rachel_Maple.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maple had hours of fun chasing the ball diving into the piles of leaves!  It was a great night for a camp fire and a simple meal of brats as we enjoyed the cool evening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/campfire.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow brings a boring drive south through Wyoming to get to Loveland CO.  From there we have a short drive into Rocky Mountain National Park.  We'll be &amp;quot;boondocking&amp;quot; without an electric hookup for three days.  Luckily the weather looks sunny so we will get to set up our solar panels.  But I'm not expecting much in the way of internet connectivity so it may be a few days before another update.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>Badlands Biking</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/badlands_biking.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-01:/badlands_biking.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It was not the Tour de France, but I had a great cheering section to keep me going!&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/badlands_road.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have often wondered what it would feel like to be in a major bike race with fans lining both sides of the road cheering you on.  Today I got a little taste of that on the badlands loop. It wasn't people cheering for me, instead it was thousands of Prairie Dogs!  And to be fair instead of chasing me down the road like the mad fans at bike races the Prairie dogs mostly just ran away.  But they make the most amazing chirping sounds that made me think they were cheering for me anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 19 mile ride I did on the road from the campground to the Wall South Dakota turnoff was made possible because I have a pretty amazing wife who told me I should hop on my bike and she would catch up with me later with camper in tow.  Not only did she have to hook everything up and pull out but she also had to empty the tanks!  I guess that is true love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/badlands_bike_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I left the campsite it was only about 36 degrees and about a mile into the ride I was wishing I had worn warmer gloves.  But as I settled into the ride my body warmed up and I didn't notice the colder temperatures at all.  Indeed it also warmed up to a nice 65 degrees pretty quickly.  It was a beautiful solitary ride, I don't think I had more than 5 cars pass me for most of the ride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At one point I did run into a bunch of cars parked on the sides of the road and it turn out that everyone was looking at the bighorn sheep.  If I was a better photographer I'm sure I would have found a way to capture all of the harsh beauty of the badlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last picture is from the turnout where Jane caught up with me.  It was called Yellow Mounds which seems to match up nicely with our first night staying in Blue Mounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/yellow_mounds.png" /&gt;
&lt;section id="lovers-leap-in-custer-state-park"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Lovers Leap in Custer State Park&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traveling in with a camper has many advantages.  Not the least of which is that after Jane caught up with me I was able to go in the camper recycle my morning coffe, and change out of my biking gear right there at the pullout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a short day of driving so it was only another 90 minutes before we were pulling into Custer State Park, one of the largest state parks in the country.  We made ourselves some tacos in the camper and then were ready to head out for an afternoon of hiking.  The trail of choice was Lovers Leap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although the first quarter of the four mile hike was steep it was well worth it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/lovers_leap1.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This. Is. Why. We. Bought. The. Camper.  How many times in your life do you get to the top of a climb and say &amp;quot;wow! just wow!&amp;quot;  That was my reaction to the pinnacle of our hike today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/lovers_leap2.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again its hard to capture the 360 degree vista from the peak of this hike!  But if you get to Custer State Park and you can do it, this is a hike not to be missed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/lovers_selfie.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last 3/4 of the hike were a much more gradual down hill slope than the first quarter but the scenery was even more beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/creekside.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of a little more than 4 mile hike I was ready to be done.  After 19 miles of biking in the morning my legs were a little tired.   But I'll say it again.  This is why we bought a camper. To see America the beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/nearing_the_end.png" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category><category term="Biking"></category></entry><entry><title>Migration West 2020</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/migration_begins.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-10-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2020-10-01:/migration_begins.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Migrating West to California.  18 Days with our Camper and many stops at National Parks&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is one reason why we bought the camper in the first place.  Take our time heading West, be in control of our environment and enjoy visits to our National Parks.  We started our trip on Jane's birthday and our first stop was in one of the towns I grew up in, Luverne Minnesota.  We spent the night at Blue Mounds State Park.  We met my aunt Jessica and Uncle John for a beer at the Take 16 brewery in town. It was great to see the town again and even more so to catch up with my favorite aunt and uncle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our route to Luverne was longer than originally planned as we made a detour through Hutchinson MN so Jane could see her dad.  Unfortunately he has had a series of strokes and is at the end of his life.  Its been sad to see him isolated from the family for the last six months due to COVID restrictions, but today Jane got to hug him and tell him she loved him in person.  We don’t know how much longer he has and we are prepared to make whatever changes to our itinerary we need to when he passes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Luverne we hopped on I90 and headed West to the Badlands of South Dakota.  We stopped for lunch at a very scenic rest area overlooking the Missouri river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/Dignity.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towing the camper in a strong north wind does nothing for your gas mileage!  So we don't make speedy progress and probably average 55 miles an hour.  On a freeway with a speed limit of 80 we were passed a lot.  This was pretty hard on Jane as she is usually doing the passing!  Once we arrived at the Badlands we quickly set up camp and headed out to do some hiking.  We did three relatively short hikes - The Notch, the Door, and the Window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/CampgroundFromNotch.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is at the end of the Notch, and you can see our campground in the distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/rattlesnakes.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is just to make sure you pay attention while you are on the trail!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Notch hike was by far the best, the other two are just board walks to some scenic views.  The most challenging part of the notch was this little ladder section.  It was so crowded when we wanted to come down that we had to find an alternate route.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/Ladder.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The campground here is a nothing to write home about.  The individual sites are just wide spots in the circle drive.  and you can't really position your camper the way you might like. Our front door opens right onto the road so we can't even roll out the awning.  But we are not here for the campground we are here for the scenery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/Camping/Migration20/sunset_campground.png" /&gt;
</content><category term="Migration20"></category><category term="Camping"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry></feed>