<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Misc</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://archive.reputablejournal.com/</id><updated>2016-08-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>The flood of 2016</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/flooding-2016.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-08-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-08-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2016-08-24:/flooding-2016.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were sitting on the screen porch last night watching the storm roll in.  In this case the 'we' was the computer science department.  There is nothing like watching the lighting show at a distance.  Just as the first person was getting ready to leave, the downpour hit.   The consensus …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We were sitting on the screen porch last night watching the storm roll in.  In this case the 'we' was the computer science department.  There is nothing like watching the lighting show at a distance.  Just as the first person was getting ready to leave, the downpour hit.   The consensus was to wait for the downpour to let up a bit before making a run for the car.  Eventually the downpour won and people sprinted.  If they would have waited for the rain to let up we would have had a slumber party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end result was a little over 8 inches of rain in about 6 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/flood1.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Luther Men's Soccer team is not likely to have a scrimmage tomorrow!  I hope the pitch can recover as we were supposed to have a lot of home games this season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/flood2.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On my ride home today I stopped in the park to take a look at the &amp;quot;prairie&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="Teaching"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving to Nikola</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/moving-to-nikola.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-20T17:38:39-05:00</published><updated>2014-04-20T17:38:39-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2014-04-20:/moving-to-nikola.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I moved this blog to Octopress in January, it was inspiring in many ways.  There were two things that slightly bugged me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Octopress is entirely too ruby based.  Rake, and all of that made me feel bad, like I was cheating on Python.  Surely there must be a similar …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I moved this blog to Octopress in January, it was inspiring in many ways.  There were two things that slightly bugged me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Octopress is entirely too ruby based.  Rake, and all of that made me feel bad, like I was cheating on Python.  Surely there must be a similar tool in the Python world I thought to myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Octopress uses markdown.  I really like my restructuredText, and its just a bit irritating to have to think about the differences when I want to do a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, this weekend I found a couple of new static blog site generators that &lt;strong&gt;were&lt;/strong&gt; python based, and after playing around with Pelican, and &lt;a href="http://getnikola.com"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; I settled on the move to Nikola.  I really like the image galleries and slideshows that are built in, and I feel like I can jump in and start hacking if something develops that I really want to change.  Plus, having already hacked a bunch of restructuredText directives, I know I can extend my blogging tool to do all kinds of fun things.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="Python"></category></entry><entry><title>wow! may 2nd! schools in the area are starting late or canceling. what a crazy spring.</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/wow-may-2nd-schools-in-the-area-are-starting-late-or-canceling-what-a-crazy-spri.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-05-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2013-05-02:/wow-may-2nd-schools-in-the-area-are-starting-late-or-canceling-what-a-crazy-spri.html</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/31.media.tumblr.com/82dbeb35b91f519132b38dceeba696fd/tumblr_mm6edoy3yM1r729pmo1_1280.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow! May 2nd!  Schools in the area are starting late or canceling.  What a crazy spring.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="cabin"></category></entry><entry><title>guest week bill amend (foxtrot)</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/guest-week-bill-amend-foxtrot.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-24T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2010-11-24T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-11-24:/guest-week-bill-amend-foxtrot.html</id><content type="html">&lt;div class='posterous_autopost'&gt;via &lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;xkcd.com&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/824/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/guest_week_bill_amend_foxtrot.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/824/"&gt;Read More &gt;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-4050658261378056812?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>steve sack - november 11, 2010</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/steve-sack-november-11-2010.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-12T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2010-11-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-11-12:/steve-sack-november-11-2010.html</id><content type="html">&lt;div class='posterous_autopost'&gt;via &lt;a href="http://comics.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;November 11, 2010 Comics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="http://comics.com/steve_sack/2010-11-11/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://c0389161.cdn.cloudfiles.rackspacecloud.com/dyn/str_strip/343590.full.gif" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="http://comics.com/steve_sack/2010-11-11/"&gt;Read More &gt;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-4154938086237541385?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>strange brew - november 1, 2010</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/strange-brew-november-1-2010.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-11-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-11-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-11-01:/strange-brew-november-1-2010.html</id><content type="html">&lt;div class='posterous_autopost'&gt;via &lt;a href="http://comics.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;November 1, 2010 Comics&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;&lt;a href="http://comics.com/strange_brew/2010-11-01/"&gt;&lt;img src="http://c0389161.cdn.cloudfiles.rackspacecloud.com/dyn/str_strip/341629.full.gif" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;a href="http://comics.com/strange_brew/2010-11-01/"&gt;Read More &gt;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-8077330036053955444?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category></entry><entry><title>27 inches of bliss</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/27-inches-of-bliss.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-07-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-07-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-07-06:/27-inches-of-bliss.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Why I'm writing this on a 27 in iMac&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm almost lost as I stare at the screen to write this post.  27 inches is a lot of screen real estate to work with, but boy do I love this new iMac!  It is fast, fast, fast.  I never thought …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Why I'm writing this on a 27 in iMac&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm almost lost as I stare at the screen to write this post.  27 inches is a lot of screen real estate to work with, but boy do I love this new iMac!  It is fast, fast, fast.  I never thought of my Macbook Pro as being a slow machine but this is crazy fast in comparison.  Typesetting my textbook project used to take minutes on the MBP, now it takes just a few seconds.  Why all this speed?  Maybe it is due to the 8 GB of memory and the 2.8 GHz Intel Core i7 processor.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The more interesting question is why am I replacing my MBP with an iMac?  The answer, in a word, is iPad.  After trying out my iPad for a few days back in April I was convinced that I would no longer need a notebook, and that my money would be better spent on a desktop.  After traveling in Europe for 28 days with the iPad as my only computer I am convinced I was right.  The iPad is the best computer ever for traveling.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;On the Plane&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Flying with an iPad is great.  We had a seven hour flight and I had loaded several movies and a bunch of TV show episodes onto my iPad, I've never had a more enjoyable long flight.  I can't sleep on planes, so it was great to be able to watch two movies and a few episodes of Merlin on the flight over.  My Bose noise canceling headphones make the experience even better as they do such a great job of blocking out the jet noise.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When I wasn't watching a video I was reading.  I had several books loaded on both iBooks and Kindle apps.  I really wish there was more selection in the iBooks store, as I'm finding they rarely have the book I want, so the kindle app gets used more frequently.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, if I wasn't watching or reading I had several games loaded to keep me entertained.  I like Scrabble, Strategery, and Fieldrunners the best, although I did play a few games of chess against tChess Lite.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;On the Ground&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While on the ground I found several apps to be incredibly useful.  WeatherBug is awesome for checking the weather forecast while away, its easy to add new cities and the coverage in the UK, Ireland, and Scandinavia is excellent. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For keeping up with the daily technology news I really like Early Edition.  It is beautiful in that it takes away all the hassle of marking things as read or whatever, every day you just get a nice newspaper like layout of the new articles that have come in since yesterday.  I love how this keeps me from getting overwhelmed with stuff when I get a few days behind.  If someone comes out with an Early Edition like reader for the mac I'm almost sure that would replace my longtime favorite, NetNewsWire, on my desktop.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Every day I also used the Photo app, it was so easy to transfer pictures from my Canon 7D to the iPad. After the transfer I could delete the really bad pictures right away, and it was great to be able to look at the photos I had taken on the iPad size screen rather than the little screen on the camera.  I really wish apple would make it possible to rate and organize pictures on the iPad that would make it even better.  Now that I'm home, I still have to go through the process of picking the best of the 1000 pictures I took and organizing them into an album.  If you could do that on the iPad then I could pick the best of each day as I go along.  I also bought PhotoForge for the iPad because there were a couple of times that I wanted to upload a photo to Facebook, and its impossible to edit the photos on Facebook using Safari on the iPad.  PhotoForge is great and very easy to use.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The other app that got a lot of use was Evernote.  prior to leaving my wife had prepared notes for each day of the trip, along with pdf maps and other info about each destination.  Although she had saved them as notes in our shared Dropbox account I found it to be much easier to drag them all into Evernote rather than the hassle of marking each document as a favorite in Dropbox so I could have offline access.  I really wish Dropbox would improve the iPad and iPhone clients to make it easier to keep things available offline.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, I wrote a blog entry almost every day of the trip using BlogPress.  I purchased an Apple Bluetooth keyboard for writing purposes and I really love it for writing longer blog entries.  For Facebook and email the onscreen keyboard is fine, but for longer writing the keyboard was awesome, and it proved to be very durable and easy to carry along in my daypack.  BlogPress itself worked like a champ.  It was a breeze to choose pictures from the Photo app to drop into the blog, and it also worked very well offline.  A lot of times I would write the blog entry when I wasn't in wi-fi range and then just post it when I found some free wi-fi.  I also like how BlogPress makes it easy to make a Facebook posting every time I publish a blog entry.  That was a great way for friends and family to know there was something new to read.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Incidentally I did not find myself wishing for a 3G iPad at all.  I was always able to find some kind of wi-fi no matter where we were.  Every hotel we stayed in had wi-fi available, not always free, but I would say in 90% of the hotels it was free.  If it wasn't free in the hotel it was not too hard to find a pub or restaurant nearby that did have it available, for the price of a coffee or drink.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-2083102877647968900?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Misc"></category><category term="mac"></category></entry></feed>