<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Reflection</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/feeds/reflection.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://archive.reputablejournal.com/</id><updated>2018-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Chapel Talk - May 7 2018</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/chapel-may-7-2018.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-05-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2018-05-07:/chapel-may-7-2018.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is the transcript of my chapel talk.  You may be able to view it &lt;a href="https://portal.stretchinternet.com/lutheradmin/portal.htm?eventId=447260&amp;amp;streamType=video"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 24:   Now that same day two of them were going to a village called Emmaus, about seven miles from Jerusalem. 14 They were talking with each other about everything that had happened …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is the transcript of my chapel talk.  You may be able to view it &lt;a href="https://portal.stretchinternet.com/lutheradmin/portal.htm?eventId=447260&amp;amp;streamType=video"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke 24:   Now that same day two of them were going to a village called Emmaus, about seven miles from Jerusalem. 14 They were talking with each other about everything that had happened. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reading for today tells of a journey, and two friends talking about everything that had happened.  So, thats my plan for today.  Although I started my journey at Luther in Fall of 1982 as a skinny freshman,  I thought I would skip over 20 years and begin in the Fall of 2002.  After a successful career in industry, I felt called to come to Luther and share my experience.  I had come to campus and gone through the interview process, I’d given my interview talk to a packed house in Olin 112.  All I really remember from that talk was that the room was hot and as I looked over my audience I saw my revered former professor Steve Hubbard nodding off in the back row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite putting Steve to sleep I thought things went well, and now back in Plymouth MN Jane and I are waiting on pins and needles to hear something from Dean Craft.  Coming to Luther to teach had been my dream since I was a junior here at Luther back in 1985.  So you can imagine the anxiety level was pretty high.  After a few extra days of waiting we threw modern theology to the wind and prayed for the lord to send us a sign!  A burning bush, a cloud shaped like a Norse head, anything!  The next day I received an email from a colleague at the University of Minnesota.  Brad, just wanted to let you know that Gustavus is going to be starting a search for a tenure track position in computer science.  Wrong sign! I shouted.  A day later the phone rang and it was Bill Craft calling with the offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my ideas and creations post a week ago I wrote about 3 teachers on my journey  who inspired me, challenged me, and changed me.  My high school teacher Mr. Weinman who knew nothing about computers  but went way out of his way to encourage a couple of nerdy teens to teach themselves to program inspires me to bring teaching resources to other high school teachers.  My Luther Professor, Walt Will,  who inspired me to become a professor in the first place.  My master’s advisor, John Carlis  who challenged me to write a textbook when I told him I was going home to Luther College.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the journey to Emmaus is not just about a couple guys on a hike, the next line of the reading tells of a stranger that joined them on their road and started chatting with them.  When I look back on my years here at Luther it will be the journeys and encounters with strangers  that became new colleagues and friends that I remember most.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have come to really love teaching students off campus.  My first  study away trip — a trip to Silicon Valley that I have done five times now — came about because an alumni wanted to teach a course on entrepreneurship. We hurriedly put the course together over November and December, and recruited 8 students... but over the Christmas break I added a last minute addition to the itinerary.  Jane and I were sitting at the Chefs table on a cruise ship and I was chatting with the stranger next to me.  I was telling him about the upcoming course which he thought sounded fantastic.  Then he dropped a bombshell, he said he worked at Pixar!  And, although visiting groups are not usually allowed he thought he could arrange something for us!  He was true to his word, and that visit turned out to be one of the real highlights of the course that year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably my favorite semester of all time at Luther will be the semester Jane and I spent with a dozen students in Malta.  We had 10 young women in the group who we very quickly began to refer to as our daughters.  We were very fortunate to get to travel with these students to Istanbul, Rome and Morocco.  It was in Marrakech , as we were walking down the street with one of our daughters that we were approached by a stranger.   I’ll give you two camels for your beautiful daughter he said with a smile and a wink.    Wait here! I said, I have 9 more daughters back at the Riad.  Some days I like to imagine the life I could have had as a camel rancher had I taken that stranger up on his offer.   A small postscript to this story:  After writing the rough draft of this talk I walked out to get the mail.  Only to find a thank you note from this very daughter.  It said “My husband and I are moving to Texas.  and I wouldn’t be ready for this next adventure if it hadn’t been for the journey’s with you two.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was on that same trip to Morocco that we had an amazing day-long journey, from Fez through the middle Atlas Mountains  - where we had a snowball fight and fed the monkeys - to the edge of the Sahara, where we boarded camels and road into the desert.  Watching the sun set over the desert is one of the most beautiful and awe inspiring sights any of us had ever seen.  That night — with no WiFi or Cell service — our Berber hosts cooked us a Tagine of beef and we sat outside with them where they played drums and sang traditional Berber songs for us.  We treated them to a rendition of "To Luther" and We will Rock You!  That night changed us all. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes when you are on a journey, it is the unplanned things that can surprise you the most.  During our stop at Ait Ben Haddou we made a dinner time decision to extend our stay so that we could visit the Ksar - The fortified city.  At breakfast, Mohammed, the owner of the Hotel Bagdhad Cafe was happy to line up a guide, also named Mohammed, for us at the last minute, giving him an unconditional recommendation as the best guide in town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At about the midway point of our climb through the Ksar our guide stopped outside his own house. "You are welcome here" he said. This is a phrase we had heard everywhere in Morocco from many different people.  It had a much different feel than "welcome to my place.” it is at once more personal, more authentic, and unconditional.  In a place where we wondered whether we really would be welcome we found it very comforting.  Maybe thats a phrase we could think about adopting here at Luther.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the tour we came upon a mosque which is still in daily use. Right next to the mosque was a synagogue, no longer in use. The history of the Berber people is very old, and interesting. At one time the majority of the Berber's were Jewish, then for a time they were Christian, but they have been Muslim for a long time.  The result for the Berbers is that they are peaceful, and very tolerant.  We want to get along with all people Mohammed told us. He went on, the problems in the world today are caused by three things: money, politics, and crazy people -- Crazy Jews, Crazy Muslims, and Crazy Christians. Most people are good and peaceful people, its a shame the crazy people have to ruin it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, as I reach the end of my journey as a Luther faculty member I have much to be thankful for and I look forward to the future with excitement.  A little over a week ago I was sitting on a plane, flying back from San Francisco.  The stranger seated next to me on this journey struck up a conversation which surprisingly lasted the entire three hour flight back to Minneapolis.  He had worked at Cargill for 17 years in their Malt division and had just recently made a long hoped for career change to become a financial planner.  I told him about my career path and that I too was making a change and was on my way back after two days of meetings with my new team at Google.  An offer had come to join this group for six months through a connection with a colleague I have only worked with online.  We have written a paper together,  we have written software together and done a joint podcast.  I wrote him a letter of recommendation for his current job at UCSD.  With this group I’ll get to do exactly what I was planning to do all along which is to work on Runestone Interactive — democratizing textbooks for the 21st century.  Only now I’ll get a bit of help which may in turn help more “Mr. Weinman’s” out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere over southwest Minnesota this stranger said to me “Wow, You’ve had an amazing journey!”  I guess you just have to keep your eyes open and be open to new opportunities when they come along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my advice to you students is to look for those strangers, take the time to chat with them and welcome them along on your journey.  You never know where it might lead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="Reflection"></category></entry><entry><title>Lifelong Luther</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/LifeLongLuther.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-04-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-04-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2018-04-25:/LifeLongLuther.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As this will be my final Ideas and Creations contribution I hope you will indulge me in a little look back over my relationship with Luther College and the teachers and professors that have made me who I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/IMG_0028.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first person I want to mention is the man …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As this will be my final Ideas and Creations contribution I hope you will indulge me in a little look back over my relationship with Luther College and the teachers and professors that have made me who I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/IMG_0028.JPG"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first person I want to mention is the man in the picture -- Charlie Weinman,  with the hairstyle and the vest you might guess this picture comes from the early 80's.  Mr. Weinman taught typing and shorthand at Luverne High School. The picture shows him in a typical pose, and I can hear his exasperated sigh at my inability to keep my eyes off the keyboard as I worked on my "perfect paragraphs."  Mr Weinman was the advisor to the annual staff as well, and his favorite saying, which I heard often, was “If you want something done right, ask a busy person”  Somewhere along the way Mr. Weinman noticed that  one of the reasons I was always so busy was because my friend and I spent an inordinate amount of time messing around on the Apple II computers our high school had just purchased.  We were teaching ourselves to program and trading games on cassette tapes. He made it his mission to help and encourage us — with the programming part.  On weekends he would drive us to programming contests all around Southwest Minnesota.  He eventually created the first programming class at the high school.  The deal was that my friends and I could take the class so we could get credit and have it on our transcript, but we were to sit in the back and keep quiet -- unless he asked for our help.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I look back on it Mr Weinman was modeling a key aspect of a Luther education — life long learning.  He also demonstrated to us  with great humor and humility that teachers don't always have all the answers.  This was a good lesson, as even today in my final semester I'm faced every day with the fact that I don't have all the answers when teaching machine learning or internet programming.  The world of computer science moves far to quickly for any of us to know it all, and we must be prepared to be lifelong learners if we are going to succeed in this field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Walt Will&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I arrived at Luther in the fall of 1982 I became a Norseman.  It was only year two for the Norsemen, but the foundations that were laid for this group in 1981 are still strong today.  Norsemen may be the only connection I have to some classmates, but I would still consider them my brothers.  It was probably my classmate,  Tim Peter, who came walking down the hall of first floor Ylvi encouraging those of us who were clueless to come to tryouts for this relatively unknown group!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/11013083_946597685364146_2856422829401261406_n.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a computer science major I was fortunate to take the majority of my classes from Dr. Walt Will.  Walt was my professor, my advisor and a great role model.   He had a wonderful dry humor and an endless supply of patience to answer my endless stream of questions in class or to just sit in his office and talk about computer science and life in general.  In the spirit of life long learning we always knew that Walt was just ahead of us (if only by a few days)  in our journey through this new field of computer science together.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walt was such a huge influence that when people would ask me about my career goals I would say "I want to come back to Luther and take Walt Will's job.”  That sounds a little harsh to my older self, but I meant it as the highest possible compliment to Walt.   I really felt that success in life would be to have the kind of impact on other students that Walt had on us. After 18 years in the computer science industry, it was ultimately Walt who paved the way for my return to Luther as a faculty member.   I remember a phone call with Walt when he told me he would be only too happy to move back to the Math department to create a position in computer science in 2003.  As I started my new career as a professor I was very lucky to have Walt down the hall to talk with and get advice.  As I’ve grown professor I've learned that I have to be myself, I'll never be Walt, I definitely don't have his patience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;John Carlis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/076C7A0B-C20B-4279-AFD2-EAB7B1330E53.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would have asked the 1990 version of Brad Miller what it was like to be a grad student at the University of Minnesota,  it would not have been a positive conversation.  Going from small-town Minnesota and Luther College to the U was a huge culture shock!  Big classes, registration lines that stretched down the stairs and around the block, professors that closed the doors to their office, it was all very foreign.   However, I would have told you about one professor that would be right at home at Luther and that was Dr. John Carlis.  I was fortunate enough to take a class from John which changed everything and led to him becoming my masters advisor and friend.  After a time or two of stopping by his office to ask questions about assignments he started making me coffee and we started talking about teaching and research and writing a one-draft thesis and singing and parenting.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John had a great sense of humor and was famous for his bad puns.  He would take two dimes out of his pocket and put them in the palm of his hand and slowly move his hand back and forth.  "Do you know what this is?" He would ask, "a pair-a-dime shift!"  Although I switched advisors for my PhD project I never stopped having coffee and conversation with John.  When I told him about coming to Luther to teach he encouraged me to write a textbook, embrace the liberal arts, and get to know people outside of CS.  At his funeral a few weeks ago I heard my story over and over from lots of former students.  John had this same kind of relationship with countless students over the years, always having the right story or the right word of encouragement at the right time. His office must have had some kind of magical time vortex because I'll never know how he could spend this much time with so many different people.  As I look back, I do not know whether I would have become a U of M graduate if had not been fortunate enough to know John Carlis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/pairadimes.jpg"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John's advice also shaped my experience as a faculty member at Luther.  Some of my favorite experiences as a faculty member come out of embracing the liberal arts:  teaching Paideia 450s with my friend Jim Martin-Schramm,  leading the Malta program, leading JTerm courses in Silicon Valley, helping to create the Data Science major are all experiences I will remember for the rest of my life.  The process of writing two paper textbooks led to the vision that has become Runestone Interactive.  My JTerm students will be happy to know that Runestone now has a mantra:  "Democratizing textbooks for the 21st century."  As I leave Luther I am super excited that I can devote my full focus and energy to Runestone., which today serves 20,000 students a day at both high schools and colleges!  I hope to make that 2 million students  in the next few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of declining enrollments, ratio imbalances, committee meetings and  program reductions its easy to forget why we do what we do.  I came to Luther 15 years ago because I felt called to share my experience and make a difference in the lives of students; just as Charlie Weinman, Walt Will, and John Carlis have made a difference in mine.  I hope I have.  My relationship with Luther is long and varied, I’m an alumni, a donor, a faculty member and a parent of an alum.  If Luther calls sometime in the future to ask me to serve in some other capacity, I hope that I can.  Soli Deo Gloria.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="Education"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>Remembering John Carlis</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/remembering-john-carlis.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-03-11T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2018-03-11:/remembering-john-carlis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm thinking of my friend and mentor on my way to his memorial service today.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants to belong, and for a young man from a small town in southwest Minnesota who went to a small liberal arts college as an undergrad, the U of M can be a pretty intimidating place -- a real "pair a dime" shift if you will.  I remember waiting in line OUTSIDE of Amundsen hall, and slowing working my way up several flights of stairs to try to get into courses that were still open once I got to the registration counter.  I may not have the name of the building right, but as John would say "never let the facts get in the way of a good story."  I remember going to classes and rather than seeing a small number of students, most of whom were my friends, all I saw was a sea of unfamiliar faces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="http://reputablejournal.com/images/pairadimes.jpg" title="Pair a Dime"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately one of the courses that I did register for was Introduction to Database Systems, taught by John Carlis.  Shortly after classes started and we were well into discussing herds of cows and various creatures and their skills and creating LDSs I found myself searching out his office to ask him some question about homework.  Once in his office we started talking, and then he made me a cup of coffee.  The conversation went well beyond drawing LDSs -- we discovered that we both liked to sing --  and he invited me to stop back again.  Soon I was stopping in his office just to chat and get a cup of coffee.  Research meetings and a TA position followed.  John became my advisor and my friend and he gave me the gift of a sense of belonging. As I look back, I wonder if I would have stayed without the cups of coffee and conversation in John's office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When our first Child was born, he gave us a present.  He had cut out and painted the letters to spell  our daughters name in his shop.  We talked about his own daughters and the challenges and joys of being a father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even years later, after I had shifted my focus to Grouplens, and started a company, he always welcomed me back.  He was still on my PhD committee, a thing he liked to remind me of frequently, especially when he wanted me to review something.  "Can you do this?  I'm still on your committee right?"  He would say with a grin.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned about building a fence around your thesis, and writing a one-draft draft thesis.  When I decided that teaching at a small college was in my future he gave me a copy of Mager's book and we talked about instructional objectives and how to become a good teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I left for Luther College he gave me another piece of advice that I will never forget.  "Write a text book," he told me.  At a small college that is a good way to publish and it will tie directly to your teaching.  Two years into my time at Luther I asked my department head, "would you like to write a book with me?"  He agreed and we found ourselves publishing the first data structures textbook using the Python programming language.  After that we wrote an introductory book on programming with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I prepare to leave Luther and move into a new project of building a sustainable small business around the Runestone Interactive textbook project I can trace the evolution of this research and writing right back to John.  The project now serves over 20,000 students a day around the world, and I frequently hear the echo of his advice in my head as I work on designing new chapters and writing new examples, and building new lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thank you John, for all the advice, the coffee, and the friendship!  More students that you will ever know have benefitted from your wisdom and hospitality.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="Education"></category><category term="Life"></category></entry><entry><title>iowa startup accelerator</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/iowa-startup-accelerator.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2014-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2014-08-06:/iowa-startup-accelerator.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been an exciting day!   I just got back from Cedar Rapids where I attended a mixer of mentors and teams at the&lt;a href="http://www.iowastartupaccelerator.com"&gt; Iowa Startup Accelerator&lt;/a&gt;.  The accelerator officially launched yesterday with 10 new teams.  There was some good local &lt;a href="http://www.cbs2iowa.com/news/features/top-stories/stories/created-corridor-ia-startup-accelerator-28963.shtml"&gt;news coverage&lt;/a&gt; and lots of excitement by the teams …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It has been an exciting day!   I just got back from Cedar Rapids where I attended a mixer of mentors and teams at the&lt;a href="http://www.iowastartupaccelerator.com"&gt; Iowa Startup Accelerator&lt;/a&gt;.  The accelerator officially launched yesterday with 10 new teams.  There was some good local &lt;a href="http://www.cbs2iowa.com/news/features/top-stories/stories/created-corridor-ia-startup-accelerator-28963.shtml"&gt;news coverage&lt;/a&gt; and lots of excitement by the teams.  Some of them are from Iowa and one team is from as far away as Australia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My role, as a mentor, will be to work with one or more teams over the next few months, giving them advice and feedback, and trying to connect them with the right people to help them grow their company.  Over the next few weeks I'll be spending some time meeting with each of the ten teams to get to know them better, and then we will see if there is a particular team that I can really help.  I hope so, tonight was fun, and the enthusiasm is infectious.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category></entry><entry><title>chapel talk - 11/4 nehemiah 13 1-3, 23-31</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/chapel-talk-11-4-nehemiah-13-1-3-23-31.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-11-05T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2013-11-05T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2013-11-05:/chapel-talk-11-4-nehemiah-13-1-3-23-31.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the text from my chapel talk yesterday.  The video (mostly of the top of my head) can be found on the &lt;a href="http://client.stretchinternet.com/client/lutheradmin.portal#"&gt;Luther Portal&lt;/a&gt;.  Make sure you go to the On Demand tab and look for me on November 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to begin today with a slightly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the text from my chapel talk yesterday.  The video (mostly of the top of my head) can be found on the &lt;a href="http://client.stretchinternet.com/client/lutheradmin.portal#"&gt;Luther Portal&lt;/a&gt;.  Make sure you go to the On Demand tab and look for me on November 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to begin today with a slightly different opening litany than we have become accustomed to:  When my friend Ann Highum asked me to switch days with her I said “sure”  after all one days reading can’t be that much harder than another.  Then I got the email from Pastor David.  It contained three very ominous words:  “these troubling texts”.  Not to mention that our reading today is from the book of Nehemiah.  Lets begin with our reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that day they read from the book of Moses in the hearing of the people; and in it was found written that no Ammonite or Moabite should ever enter the assembly of God, 2 because they did not meet the Israelites with bread and water, but hired Balaam against them to curse them—yet our God turned the curse into a blessing. 3 When the people heard the law, they separated from Israel all those of foreign descent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, discrimination, xenophobia, that sounds troubling enough to get started.  We’ll come back to versus 23-31 in a moment.  This is not your typical sunday school reading.  Who are the Ammonites or the Moabites?  What did they do to deserve getting kicked out?  I think we might need a bit of context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it turns out that the book of Nehemiah is essentially a blog written by Nehemiah himself, who was the cupbearer for King Ataxerxes.  So I thought as a public service I would try to give some context to todays reading by condensing Nehemiah’s blog posts into a series of tweets.   A sort of Twitter translation of the bible with commentary from yours truly. Nehemiah himself goes by @cupbearer21 in case you want to follow him on Twitter later today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Posts from the month of Chislev:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brother Hanani came to Susa today, brought visitors from Judah&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OMG the wall of Jeursalem is broken and the gates destroyed by fire!  #JerusalemFire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve been weeping, fasting, and praying for days.  Still distraught over the fire in Jerusalem.  #WoeIsMe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we get some insight into the incredible guilt and potentially inflated sense of self importance that @cupbearer21 must feel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can’t help but feel that the #JerusalemFire is my fault!   Me and my family must have offended @God.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Now we skip to the month of Nisan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AtaXerxes told me to buck up.  I guess he can tell I’m still sad over #JerusalemFire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just days later we get the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Holy career path! @ataxerxes granted my request to go to Judah and rebuild the walls of Jerusalem!   #ClimbTheRoyalLadder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to be sure that he does not encounter opposition on the journey he tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anyone doubts me here’s a link to letters from @ataxerxes granting me safe passage and timber from the royal forest.  #TheKingsGotMyBack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Nehemiah’s glee is short lived, just days later we learn:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curses! @TobiahtheAmmonite is not happy with me. He will try to foil my plans for rebuilding the wall!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ahh, so we have a bit of dramatic foreshadowing on this deal with the Ammonites.  Our story continues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snuck out tonight to inspect the walls on my own.  #ThisPlaceIsAMess&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the inspection, its time for the work on the walls to begin in earnest, but Nehemiah needs workers so he tweets out a plea for help:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Join me! we are going to rebuild the walls!  The hand of my God is gracious!
     To which there are hundreds of replies of the form @cupbearer21 count me in!  @cupbearer21 tools ready to go, The hashtag #RebuildTheWalls was definitely trending that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But not everyone was on board with Nehemiah’s plans:  @SanballatTheHoronite and @TobiahTheAmmonite and @GeshemTheArab who basically responded &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;@cupbearer21 WT——H 
@cupbearer21 Who do you think you are? Are you rebelling against the King?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, Nehemiah we can tell work is proceeding by the status updates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High priest @eliashib doing good work on the sheep gate
Sons of @hassenaah rebuilt the fish gate today&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and so on with tweet after tweet of progress from around the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course in typical twitter flamewar fashion we see some retweets from our old friends @SanballatTheHoronite and @TobiahTheAmmonite&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ha!  what are these feeble Jews doing?    Do they think they can rebuild the wall in a day1?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And from Tobiah, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That stone wall they are building — any fox would break it down!  #I’llHuffAndI’llPuff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which Nehemiah replies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh @God, do not blot out the sins of @Tobiahtheammonite  #FireyPitForYouDude&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some days later:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big day today!!  Walls back to half their original height!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But even with all of that progress those darn Ammonites stirring up trouble again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emergency! We need families NOW to guard the walls against @sanballat and his ilk.  #NeedMoreSpears.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And although you might think I'm making this one up, Nehemiah has been so busy that he tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to smell, its been weeks since I put down my spear and changed my clothes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After all that, Nehemiah shows that he is a guy who can get things done.  After just 52 days he tweets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At last, the wall is done!  #PartyAtMyHouse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the wall rebuilt, Nehemiah gets an interesting assignment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From @God:  Hey! @cupbearer21, You should use your analytics and do a genealogical and demographic analysis of the people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point there are several chapters of names of Levites, and prophets and lineages of various families.  Clearly ancestry.com could have saved a bunch of time.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, rebuilding the wall is clearly the signature accomplishment of Nehemiah,  But even with all of his success as governor, Nehemiah doesn't take advantage of food and land allotments that were allowed him, because there was already such a great burden on the people.  He also made the other nobles and officials forgive all outstanding debts and ordered them to return all land and money that had been taken as taxes so the people would be able to feed themselves and their families.  To keep everyone happy he organizes covenant day which is summarized in the following tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covenant day!  #TithingIsGood  #OfferingsRock #FirstBornSonsToGod #FirstOfEverythingToGod&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which brings us again to Chapter 13 and these troubling tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much reform is needed @Elishib and @Tobiah have made a mess of things  #NoMixedMarriages #KeepMarriagePure&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kicked out the foreigners  #KeepTheIsreaelitesPure  #PureJerusalem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And in what must have felt like the ultimate victory for old Nehemiah:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chased @Jehoidia son-in-law of @SanballatTheHoronite away! He is gone from the city!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which I now might imagine a response out of the future:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From @JCSofG,   Wait, What!? No No No!  #EatWithTaxCollectorsAndSinners!  #BadNehemia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, does our story for today all come down to Nehemiah getting his revenge on the Ammonites for trying to thwart his efforts to rebuild the walls of Jerusalem?  It sure sounds like it. The sad thing is that In many ways this story seems all too familiar.  Take out Nehemiah and Insert the name of your favorite ruler: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humble beginnings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great accomplishments and rise to power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power goes to the head&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stupid policies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whats maybe more interesting to me is why this particular verse is the verse for the day, with all of the good things Nehemiah did, why highlight this one idiotic policy? Maybe simply to remind us that tolerance is a good thing even when times are tough.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve spent a lot of time this last week trying to answer the question, where’s the grace in this story? I think maybe for us and for Nehemiah it really does come down to his final tweet:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember me @God for the good I have done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category></entry><entry><title>john riedl tribute</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/john-riedl-tribute.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2013-09-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2013-09-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2013-09-02:/john-riedl-tribute.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;This is the short tribute speech I gave last Friday at the University of Minnesota.  Actually, I had to edit my speech to be shorter than this, so I thought I would just post this longer version, plus it contains some fun old images I dug up that I didn't …&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;!--?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;This is the short tribute speech I gave last Friday at the University of Minnesota.  Actually, I had to edit my speech to be shorter than this, so I thought I would just post this longer version, plus it contains some fun old images I dug up that I didn't get to show.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonelake/10693282536/" title="6e6018d47f07c38ea8a7ee2421e396ba by bnmnetp, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7367/10693282536_78e4e228a2_n.jpg" width="320" height="213" alt="6e6018d47f07c38ea8a7ee2421e396ba"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 14px;"&gt;Hi, I'm Brad Miller.  For those of you who don't know me, I was one of John's PhD students, and a co-founder of Net Perceptions, but more importantly he was someone I admired, respected, and called my friend.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style="font-size: 14px;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 14px;"&gt;Now, I  still use Instant Messaging quite a bit, and its a way that John and I connected over the years.  But,  its a bit disconcerting that when I look at my Buddy list today I still see John Riedl in my list.  The problem is, he's not  "Offline," or "Away," He's "Idle!"  So, somewhere out there, or UP there, he's still logged in and on IM. Of course its on his gtalk account so maybe maybe google is expanding their mission beyond "the world".  Anyway,  I have this irresistible urge to have a conversation with him.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 14px;"&gt;I hope this imaginary conversation conveys the amazing sense of Humor he always had for whatever we were doing.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;br style="font-family: Arial;" /&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonelake/10693235065/" title="Screenshot 2013-08-25 17.07.27 by bnmnetp, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3782/10693235065_6670fb784f_o.png" width="194" height="62" alt="Screenshot 2013-08-25 17.07.27"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Dude, time to chat?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Just a sec, I'm trying to explain collaborative filtering to the big guy&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  I suppose I can wait.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  OK, I'm back…. for someone omnipotent, he's little slow on his basic probability and stats.  He had this cool idea that based on some sins that you had avoided in your past, we might recommend other sins to avoid.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Wow, we haven't had a negative rating problem like that since "Cleveland!"  But really rating sins? on a likert scale? do you think that will work?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  No, I think this would be a much better app to test out some of our hypotheses on implicit ratings.  Anyway,   What's up.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Just missing you.  Remember the first class I had from you? It was Fall 1993, CS8101 - Distributed Systems.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Wow, that was a long time ago.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Remember the project that Dave Truckenmiller and I did?  We designed a Distributed Version Control System, for SCoNes.   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Scones?  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:   Devices on a Seldomly Connected Network.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  HA!  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:&lt;/strong&gt; And remember our DRIP protocol  (Distributed Replicated Information Pile)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yeah, that was good project, and you got your A, but I think I should go back and revise your grade down.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Why?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Well if you think about it,  in the end you guys got it wrong by requiring locking.   I think we had a long talk about merge versus lock.  Clearly the people in the merging camp like git and mercurial got it right in the end.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Ok, but they did come to the party almost 15 years later!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Fair point, turns out its pretty hard to revise a grade after all these years anyway.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Do you remember the cease and desist letter we got from the Better Business bureau lawyers?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial; font-size: 14px;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  That was great!  Maybe if &lt;em&gt;someone&lt;/em&gt; hadn't photoshopped the BBB torch into some bizarre mashup of a  BNC connector with a computer on the top, and then put it on a website, this never would have happened!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonelake/10693236715/" title="ba6d3452e69c2bfd735df2d6b4d76448 by bnmnetp, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7323/10693236715_2f75194de9_o.jpg" width="185" height="185" alt="ba6d3452e69c2bfd735df2d6b4d76448"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  I think it had more to do with our naming the server the Better Bit Bureau!  I thought I might be the first PhD student to flunk out of the U for copyright infringement.  Plus we only had like 10 users at the time, so really!! Who cared?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  You were worried!?  I didn't even have tenure yet!  I Remember that they told us we could use any one of their 'B' words, but not two of the three together.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yeah, luckily choosing a new name was "just a simple matter of coding"&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Remember the ultimate test newsgroup for the Grouplens Usenet trial?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Ha,  how could I forget that?  I know you and Joe were a lot more partial to rec.food.recipes, but you can't beat alt.sex.grouplens.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;: Uh John,  You don't think they are, you know, monitoring your transmissions up there.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Well, I haven't &lt;em&gt;seen&lt;/em&gt; any guys from the NSA wandering around.  Plus, what are they going to do to me?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  I worked so hard to get the emacs gnus reader working.   Hours of fun hacking in lisp.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yeah, I never could understand those people that used vi!  Emacs rules man!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  We worked so hard on that trial, and I had so many hypotheses that were totally wrong.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yep, but remember I always told you that a negative result is still a result.  And there is nothing more cruel in the world than the murder of a theory by a cold, hard, ugly fact.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  You said it.  I can't tell you how much comfort I got from that.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me:  &lt;/strong&gt;Hey, speaking of names do you remember that particularly long afternoon of trying to come up with a company and product name?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  How could I forget.  You were the worst!  "Villagent"  who would buy software from a bunch of Vigalantes!?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yeah, that was not one of my finer ideas.  It was cool that GroupLens got to live on through a few product cycles at least.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/bonelake/10693277824/" title="f8d329ab455943f3bcaf122e6c9736b0 by bnmnetp, on Flickr"&gt;&lt;img src="http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7329/10693277824_a9df1562f9_o.jpg" width="294" height="165" alt="f8d329ab455943f3bcaf122e6c9736b0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  I think our  release code names were the best.  - Photuris was my favorite.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  Yeah the Firefly killer.  We showed those Media Lab guys a thing or two.  But I might have to go with Cleveland, just because it drove Steven crazy.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Cleveland, I remember that!  We even had T-shirts made up for that one.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me&lt;/strong&gt;:  well, I'd like to chat more but they only gave me 3-5 minutes for this tribute.  Just one last question for you.  Why isn't your status Away?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;John&lt;/strong&gt;:  Thats easy, Brad.  I'm not.  I live on in your memories, I live on through Eric, Karen, and Kevin, and I live on through you and the rest of my students.  Don't worry, I'll always be with you in spirit.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style="font-family: Arial;"&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category></entry><entry><title>dear apple</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/dear-apple.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-09-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-09-17:/dear-apple.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Apple,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You lost a sale today.  I know its just one less iPhone you are going to sell, and in the grand scheme of things does not amount to anything.  I suppose its not really your fault, and as a loyal Apple customer its much easier for me to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dear Apple,&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You lost a sale today.  I know its just one less iPhone you are going to sell, and in the grand scheme of things does not amount to anything.  I suppose its not really your fault, and as a loyal Apple customer its much easier for me to blame AT&amp;amp;T than you.  Still, it makes me sad to have to tell you this.  I waited as long as I could for AT&amp;amp;T to expand their network in my direction. I've hung on every Verizon rumor for two years.  Finally after enduring a year of carrying my iPod touch in the same pocket as the mind numbingly horrible Motorola Crush I bought an HTC Desire yesterday.  Android!! I never thought I would see the day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Here's whats even worse, I like it!  It has some great apps Gmail, Calendar, and many apps that I already love on my iPod Touch and iPad:  Dropbox, Evernote, 1Password, Kindle, Facebook, Twitter, Weather, Stocks, and a 5, yes 5, megapixel camera!  I already love the gps, so the location aware apps work, I love the WiFi and the Bluetooth.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm going to miss OmniFocus, but I carry around my Ipad almost everywhere I go so I don't think I'll miss it that much.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So Apple, I'll remain a loyal customer, at least for now.  I'm going to continue to develop my app for the iPad, I still love my iMac and my MacBook Pro.  But if US Cellular comes out with a decent family data plan in the next month or so you may lose two more sales as the rest of my family follows me into the smartphone world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-7948861859540801287?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="mac"></category></entry><entry><title>ebook man is cleaning out the library</title><link href="https://archive.reputablejournal.com/ebook-man-is-cleaning-out-the-library.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2010-08-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-08-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:archive.reputablejournal.com,2010-08-19:/ebook-man-is-cleaning-out-the-library.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So today I sat in my office and looked over at my library of books, probably about 700 books all together.  The top half of the library contains my cookbook collection and lots of other non-fiction books.  The bottom half is largely science fiction, some paperbacks that I've had for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So today I sat in my office and looked over at my library of books, probably about 700 books all together.  The top half of the library contains my cookbook collection and lots of other non-fiction books.  The bottom half is largely science fiction, some paperbacks that I've had for 30 years,  The Lord of the Rings trilogy for example.  There were also several large stacks of books on the floor because the shelves are full.  Jane is wanting me to do something to get the books off the floor.  Even though she doesn't spend that much time in my office so I don't know why it bothers her, but she's right the piles have been accumulating and its time to do something.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Suddenly it hit me, I could let all of the paperbacks go.  I've been saving them for years because they are my favorites and maybe I'll read them again, or maybe I just like to look at the shelves and see my old favorites sitting there. I'm not sure what the precise reason is, whatever it is I'm over it.  I just realized that if I did want to read them again, I would no longer want to do it by holding a real book in my hand.  I realized that just like all of my old '80s music that I had on cassette tape these are relics of my past, and if I did want to read them again I would be happier to download them to my iPad and read them in the kindle app or iBooks.  But, fat chance that the iBooks store would have any of these old favorites.  I prefer the iPad over the dedicated Kindle because it saves me one device.  Plus until now the kindle required cell coverage that I don't have.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So, here, for posterity, and maybe to remind me in the future if I come back and read this post instead of staring at bookshelves, is a random walk through the lower half of my library. If you have suggestions for what I can do with the paperbacks let me know.  If you read this list and have suggestions for other authors you think I would like, definitely let me know.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rober Sawyer, every book ever written by him except for the current WWW series which I bought in electronic form from the beginning.  Factoring Humanity, Calculating God, the Hominid Series, great ideas&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Isaac Asimov, The robot books, and the entire foundation series.  These books took me through college.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Stephen R. Donaldson, the Thomas Covenant Chronicles.  Covenant is still one frustrating guy whenever I think about these books.  Although I notice that there are some new additions to the series that are out in eBook form...&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dan Simmons, the Hyperion, Endymion series.  The Shrike was one scary monster.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;David Brin, Despite the absolutely dismal movie the Postman is still a favorite in how it forshadowed the web.  I also have some Brin on the upper half of the library, The Transparent Society is an excellent book to get you thinking about privacy in the digital age.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Orson Scott Card, the Enders Game series... I loved all of these books, and I even like some of the more recent ones where he goes back and fills in some missing pieces from the perspective of other characters.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Connie Willis, The Doomesday Book is awesome as are many of her other stories although none have captivated me as much as that one.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Frank Herbert, The Dune series of course.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Robert Heinlien, Stranger in a Strange Land and others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mary Doria Russel, The Sparrow.  This is one of my all time favorite books, in fact I even made my Paideia students read it last year.  I'm sure they thought I was off the deep end for making them read Science Fiction in a serious class like Paideia but Oh well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Robert Russo, not science fiction but a great writer.  I like all of his books, but teaching at a small college, I get tears in my eyes from laughing so hard when I read Straight Man.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;And speaking of non-science fiction books, Jon Hassler, this guy captures small town midwest living so well.  From Staggerford to Rookery Blues they are amazing.  I miss him, and I miss Connie Helgen who recommended him to me.  After our trip to Ireland this summer I've been longing to go back and read a Green Journey again, but I just checked and its not available in the Kindle store.  Horrors!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;James Halperin, The Truth Machine, and I just read an article this morning about a group out in california that is using MRI as a new lie detector.  Anyway, read this book.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Roger Zelazny, the whole Amber Series, kind of a disfunctional family but the whole series is fun to read.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;John Grisham, hmmm why did I save all of these??&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Carl Sagan, Contact.  I read this way before the Jodi Foster movie.  That was just a bonus for a young geek who loved her in the after school specials.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;J. R. R. Tolkien, a boxed set of the Hobbit and the Lord of the Rings.  I don't think I can part with these.  I still remember reading these late at night with a flashlight under my blanket.  I've still never been able to make it through the Silmarillion though.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Douglass Adams, such a loss, The Hitchhikers Guide to the Galaxy series.  I swear I can open up any of these books to a random page and start reading and I'll be laughing in no time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Neal Stephenson, Snow Crash and Cryptonomicon.  I've never had the energy to make it through the Quicksilver books, but I have Anathem on my iPad so we'll see.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gordon R. Dickson, Dorsai, the Chantry Guild, The Final Encyclopedia&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Larry Niven, the Ringword Books, and other books with Jerry Pournelle (a Mote in God's Eye)  I still remember looking forward to reading Pournelle's Chaos Manor column in Byte magazine every month&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Robert Charles Wilson, Spin, Darwinia, The Chronoliths, and others.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Vernor Vinge, A Fire Upon the Deep, a Deepness in the Sky&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ursula K. LeGuin, The Dispossessed, and the Earthsea books.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mary Stewart, The Crystal Cave series that retells the legend of King Arthur.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I also discovered a rather interesting section on the shelves devoted to historical fiction, but I'll leave that for another time.  I just wanted to mention it in case you've concluded that I'm hopelessly one dimensional.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I would also say that I've discovered that computer science reference books work very well as ebooks.  I've been teaching myself to program my iPad and I have several good references in electronic form.  Its nice to have them open on my big screen, and its easy to find examples when you can search.&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-1345374799381159586?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Reflection"></category><category term="books"></category></entry></feed>