<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>A Reputable Journal - Tech</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/feeds/tech.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/</id><updated>2018-03-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>A Detour on our Cording Cutting Journey</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/Cutting%20the%20cord%20is%20not%20as%20easy%20as%20you%20think.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-03-03T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2018-03-03:/PelicanBlog/Cutting the cord is not as easy as you think.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wonder how much data we have used this period? I asked my wife as we were streaming Premier League football on YouTube Tv at 4K resolution on Saturday morning.  A few minutes later I had found the right page and was staring at a bright red bar graph that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I wonder how much data we have used this period? I asked my wife as we were streaming Premier League football on YouTube Tv at 4K resolution on Saturday morning.  A few minutes later I had found the right page and was staring at a bright red bar graph that showed I had already used 60% of my 999 GB limit with 66% of the month still remaining!  Maybe this cord cutting idea isn't really going to save us very much money after all I thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got to this point because a few weeks ago I saw an ad for Hulu Live.  We watch most of our TV on Hulu because I love that for just a few bucks a month I don't have to even fast forward through commercials.  For $40 a month we could get Hulu Live which promised us live streaming of all the major networks as well as NBC Sports Network -- the channel that account for 90% of our live viewing.  So, we looked at our DirecTV bill of $170 per month and thought wow we could really save! So we signed up for the free week and gave it a try.  It was the last week of the Winter Olympics so it was a great trial of live streaming, but less so for watching network series.  I'm not a huge fan of the Hulu interface as it seems to go out of its way to make it hard to find the live shows you want, unless its something you watch very regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The challenges started when we considered how we could best use the Hulu service at our lake house over the summer.  It turns out that Hulu is more like your cable company than you might think.  Smart TVs, Apple TVs, and gaming consoles are all considered "living room devices". This means that they will use geolocation to update your home market.  Something that Hulu only allows you to do 4 times per year.  I'm not sure what happens after that, but I'm guessing you are locked into whatever that location was.  So we would really need 2 subscriptions, one for each home.  Not quite the savings we anticipated but not horrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next challenge came with the end of the Olympics.  While Hulu had tons of NBC Olympic coverage, as soon as the games were over we lost our access to any live NBC programming.  This turns out to be because we happen to live in Northeast Iowa and Hulu does not have a deal with KWWL, our nearest Iowa NBC affiliate, and the same for CBS.  So much for the live streaming of network television in Northeast Iowa.  This might not be a big issue except that Jane likes to have the today show on in the background when she is at home in the mornings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started looking more closely at DirecTV now (same problems with the affiliates) as well as YouTube TV.  YouTube would at least show us the Chicago local stations.  But after some investigation and experimentation it seems that YouTube TV has two pretty big advantages.  First it just lets me set a home address to whatever I want.  And second using the address of our lake house we get the Minneapolis affiliates!  This is really perfect as we'll be Minneapolis residents in September and this will let us get a jump on the local news.  Not to mention we can watch the Minnesota United away games on Fox North!  At the lake we are also used to watching the Minneapolis stations as we get them with our antenna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, YouTube for live TV and back to just using Hulu with the no commercial option for watching our favorite shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us back to the data usage.  Having used 60% of the data in only 30% of the month would make one think they are going to need more data.  So I go online to chat with a Mediacomm representative to see how much that is going to cost me.  The first suggestion would have cost me another $64 / month.  But that package included Gigabit speeds.  Much as I would enjoy having that badge of honor, I don't need that kind of bandwidth at home.  But they must be trained to go there first.  Only after I asked about the 200 MB and 2TB package was I told that that would cost me an additional $24 per month.  Then, after a short pause I was told that if I BUNDLED CABLE along with my Internet and the phone service (that I already don’t use) I would be even less than what I am paying now!  Ok, so I can hook up to cable and double my bandwidth and limits!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, the agony!  I can’t tell you how little I like Mediacomm!  Yet I can save money and get better service by becoming their cable customer again. And, best of all I don’t even have to sign a contract, I’m free to cancel at any time, or check on the latest package deals in a year when my subscription would be slated to increase by $20 per month.  No worries there as I won’t be a customer in a year.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’m going to save money and get better service, why do I feel so dirty?  We started this exercise as a way to cut the cord to save money and stop supporting crazy TV providers.  Along the way we found out that online providers are learning the tricks from their predecessors, and then we come full circle to having a cable box in the house. I’d like to put it in a corner and not even connect it to a TV but my dear wife keeps reminding me that we can save another $35/month because we won’t need YouTube TV if we have that cable box.  We’ll see, I don’t know how many channels we’ll get and whether our package will include NBCSN…. Time for a shower.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="Tech"></category></entry><entry><title>My Life in the Computer History Museum</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/my-life-in-the-chm.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-01-18T00:00:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2018-01-18:/PelicanBlog/my-life-in-the-chm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Its been six or eight years since I've taken a group of students to the Computer History Museum, and am I ever glad that I made the stop this time.  The museum has changed a lot over the years and this was by far the best visit ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Its been six or eight years since I've taken a group of students to the Computer History Museum, and am I ever glad that I made the stop this time.  The museum has changed a lot over the years and this was by far the best visit ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part of the &amp;quot;ancient&amp;quot; history of computing (up to the late 1970's) was really well done, but I noticed that I couldn't stop myself from snapping pictures of computers from then on.  I realized that I was in fact taking pictures of the machines that I have personally worked on or used for fun over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="atari-game-console"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Atari Game console&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/Atari.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you ever play tank battle on one of these?  I think its safe to say that this was the first game console I ever used.  Notice the lovely woodgrain finish, and the switch to change between black and white and color TVs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="apple-ii"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apple II&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/AppleII.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Apple II was the first computer I ever programmed.  Lets face it, if you couldn't write a little basic, the Apple II was pretty useless.  I first encountered the Apple II in the AV room of my high school in the spring of my Freshman year in 1979.  I never looked back.  Hacking the Lemonade Stand game was my first stab at modifying someone else's code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="trs-trash-80"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TRS (Trash) 80&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/TRS80.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course this is the computer I wanted for my own.  It was less expensive than the Apple, black and white and ran BASIC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="teletype"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TeleType&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/TeleType.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luverne high school, like many schools ofthe day, was connected to MECC (Minnesota Educational Computing Consortium)  By 300 baud modem we connected to a big CDC computer running somewhere in the twin cities.  We could play Star Trek against other high school students or use a primitive chat program where, even in 1980, every third high school girl went by an online name of &amp;quot;FoxyLady&amp;quot;  Of course back than it was FOXYLADY as lower case characters were not invented yet.  This particular specimin actually only ran at 110 baud and was pretty much out of use by the tie I got into high school   Using this seemed like a huge pain, but at least I can say that I missed the card punch era!  Beyond basic on the AppleII we could write programs in Pascal on the MECC computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-pet-trapezoid"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The PET Trapezoid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/PET.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got to Luther College and went to my first General Physics lab, these were the computers that greeted us.  Programmable in basic, and easy to interface to simple lab equipment using the basic commands PEEK and POKE to set and read memory locations that were mapped to the I/O devices.  We could also use the PET computers to do accurate timing, as long as you were able to convert from the unit of a &amp;quot;Jiffy&amp;quot; to seconds.  As I recall there were 60 Jiffies in a second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="data-general-soul-of-a-new-machine"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Data General - Soul of a New Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/DataGeneral.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I never actually used a Data General computer, but during my first year of college I read Tracy Kidder's book &lt;em&gt;The Soul of a New Machine&lt;/em&gt;, this book had such a huge influence on me, it totally cemented my career path toward computer computer science.  I loved this book so much that I kept it and had it in my office atLuther after I became a professor.  When Kidder came to Luther to give the opening convocation speech a few years ago to talk about his latest book &lt;em&gt;Mountains beyond Mountains&lt;/em&gt;, I was able to meet him and have him autograph my 30+ year old paperback.  He actually looked quite surprised that I had a paperback that old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="pdp-11"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;PDP 11&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/PDP11.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another early computer I encountered at Luther, in the MRI lab, was an LSI-11, this was the Heathkit replica of this PDP-11.  The lab had an even older PDP-8 but the museum didn't have one of those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="commodore-64"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Commodore 64&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/Comodore64.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I worked on the most in the MRI lab at Luther was a Commodore64.  We had a cartridge version of the programming language FORTH that I used to write a program to collect data from the Analog to Digital Converter.  I remember being shocked that we were using this incredibly inexpensive computerto control a $10,000 data collection device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="apollo"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apollo&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/Apollo.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the summer of 1985 I had the amazing opportunity to do an internship at Amoco research center in Tulsa Oklahoma.  I was tasked with writing benchmarks to test various implementations of Lisp for the IBM PC.  I remember that I had the first PC/AT in the building.  But more interesting was my friend Jay's Apollo.  I think we called this mini-computers back then, today we would think of them as workstations.  What I remember most about the Apollo was the speed of it, and the graphics capabilities!  This was the very early days of windows and mice, and I recall that Jay had a program that he could start up on the Apollo that would make it look like chunks of your display were breaking loose and falling to the bottom of your screen.  It was hilarious the first time it happened to us.  That summer was also my first exposure to using a 3270 green screen terminal.  Sadly I didn't seen one at the computer history museum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/IBMPC.png" /&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="apple-lisa-and-macintosh"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apple Lisa and Macintosh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/Mac_Lisa.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jay also had a Lisa in his home office!  I couldn't wait to graduate and make some money so I could have one of my own.  Of course by the time Jane and I got married just a year later the Lisa was a thing of the past and so we got a Mac Plus instead!  I still have this computer in my office at Luther.  It still boots from a floppy and runs Microsoft's flight simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-cdc-6600"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The CDC 6600&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/CDC6600.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started work at Control Data's Energy Management Systems division in 1986 I was awed by the giant cooled computer room.  There were lots of giant water cooled Cyber computers in there for the newer customers, but amongst all of those newere Cybers was this little old CDC6600 computer than was running an older version of the software.  If it scares you that our electrical grid was controlled by one of these don't worry, they were solid work horses for many years.  What I remember most about the 6600 was that there was a little program that made the two CRT's look like eyes, and then one of them would wink at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="symbolics-lisp-machine"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Symbolics Lisp Machine&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/Symbolics.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years at CDC I managed to manuever my way into an AI group. A lot of high-end AI programming was done in Lisp in those days and the Symbolics was &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; machine to have if you really wanted to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="silicon-graphics"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Silicon Graphics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/SGI.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the Symbolics we switched to running more general purpose Unix workstations.  CDC was reselling SGI computers under the label of &amp;quot;Personal Iris&amp;quot;  I taught myself some very early graphics in what eventually became OpenGL on these machines.  This began a life long love of using Unix.  I spent many extra hours on the Iris compiling emacs and other early open source programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-palm-pilot"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Palm Pilot&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img class="m-image" src="/images/ComputerHistory/PalmPilot.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last bit of nostalgia I captured at the museum was this first generation Palm Pilot!  I remember that when Net Perceptions officially launched our product it was at the Agenda conference in Phoenix Arizona.  They were also launching the Palm Pilot at that same conference.  What I remember most about this was the brilliant marketing they did.  First, they had preloaded a bunch of Palm Pilots with the conference schedule.  Second, they had a bunch of &amp;quot;old ladies&amp;quot; demonstrating how easy they were to use.  They showed you the Grafiti writing system, how to add meetings, and they took your credit card with the promise that you could use one for the duration of the conference and if you didn't want it after that they wouldn't charge your card.  I'm pretty sure every single person kept theirs.  This was the first of a very long line of PDAs that I have owned over the years. I could probably do a whole post just on those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visiting the Computer History Museum was educational, and a great trip down memory lane for me.  If you are ever in Mountain View and have a few hours I would highly recommend you plan to spend couple hours exploring!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="Teaching"></category><category term="Travel"></category></entry><entry><title>aquamacs 2.0 elisp fun</title><link href="https://bnmnetp.github.io/PelicanBlog/aquamacs-2-0-elisp-fun.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2009-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-07-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Brad Miller</name></author><id>tag:bnmnetp.github.io,2009-07-03:/PelicanBlog/aquamacs-2-0-elisp-fun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;While waiting for the white smoke to emerge on Textmate 2.0, I decidedto revisit an old friend.  It turns out the emacsen have been busysince I've been using TextMate.  Aquamacs 2.0 is a great Cocoa port ofEmacs 23.  Not sure whether I should call it a port since …&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"&gt;While waiting for the white smoke to emerge on Textmate 2.0, I decidedto revisit an old friend.  It turns out the emacsen have been busysince I've been using TextMate.  Aquamacs 2.0 is a great Cocoa port ofEmacs 23.  Not sure whether I should call it a port since emacsofficially supports the OS X operating system.The first thing I did was check out some of the old modes I used touse.  AucTeX, GNUs are both packaged with emacs now.   The SQL mode that comes withis great and "just works" with mysql and postgresql. There is goodsupport for Python and of course HTML. Two minor gliches in thoseareas that I wish I could fix:&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;I cannot get MMM (multi-major-mode) to work properly.  I wouldreally like to have both HTML and Javascript colorized properly whenI'm working on my Django projects.  If anyone has any advice ongetting MMM to work right in emacs 23 I would really appreciate apointer.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Completion in iPython does not work right.  Instead of completingin the ipython shell it just indents more.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;In addition to some old friends I discovered a bunch of new modes thatare really nice.  JDE for Java development, Muse for creating lecturenotes in a personal wiki style.  In addition Muse lets you publish amarkup style format really easily in lots of differnt output formats.I've been a big fan of using Pandoc with TextMate over the last fewyears, but Muse is every bit as nice.One thing lacking in Muse was the ability to quickly bold or ital ortt some part of the text I'm working on.  So I decided to dust off mylisp coding ability and cook up my own.  The result is shown below.  Ithink it is a nice example of a lot of what you need to do in writingbasic lisp extensions for any text processing mode.  I'd be happy toget comments on how to improve this.The idea of these simple commands is that pressing cmd-b should boldthe word the cursor is currently on, or the region (if there is one)or simply insert **|** when the cursor is not on a word.   It alsotook some research to figure out how to bind a function to the commandkey. (side note: I've finally gotten comfortable with using the optionkey for meta in emacs.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;pre style="overflow:auto;" class="prettyprint lang-el"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(defun muse-bold-word ()&lt;br /&gt;  (interactive)&lt;br /&gt;  (muse-wrap-with-string "**" 2)&lt;br /&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(defun muse-ital-word ()&lt;br /&gt;  (interactive)&lt;br /&gt;  (muse-wrap-with-string "*" 1)&lt;br /&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(defun muse-tt-word () &lt;br /&gt;  (interactive)&lt;br /&gt;  (muse-wrap-with-string "=" 1)&lt;br /&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(defun muse-wrap-with-string (str len)&lt;br /&gt;  (if mark-active&lt;br /&gt;      (progn&lt;br /&gt; (kill-region (point) (mark))&lt;br /&gt; (let ((myword (car kill-ring)))&lt;br /&gt;   (insert (concat str myword str) )))&lt;br /&gt;    (let ((myStr (thing-at-point 'word)))&lt;br /&gt;      (if myStr&lt;br /&gt;   (let ((myBounds (bounds-of-thing-at-point 'word)))&lt;br /&gt;     (kill-region (car myBounds) (cdr myBounds))&lt;br /&gt;     (insert (concat str myStr str)))&lt;br /&gt; (progn&lt;br /&gt;   (insert (concat str str))&lt;br /&gt;   (goto-char (- (point) len)) ) ) ))&lt;br /&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;(define-key muse-mode-map `[(,osxkeys-command-key b)] 'muse-bold-word)&lt;br /&gt;(define-key muse-mode-map `[(,osxkeys-command-key i)] 'muse-ital-word)&lt;br /&gt;(define-key muse-mode-map `[(,osxkeys-command-key k)] 'muse-tt-word)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="blogger-post-footer"&gt;&lt;img width='1' height='1' src='https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/tracker/2759017781463016019-7610258374161196053?l=blog.bonelakesoftware.com' alt='' /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Tech"></category><category term="emacs"></category></entry></feed>